<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The first, last, or, The formal hypocrite further from salvation (as to the way of God's ordinary working) than the prophane sinner being the substance of several sermons preached in course at a lecture in the countrey / by J.O. ...</title>
            <author>Oldfield, John, 1627?-1682.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1666</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 188 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 78 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53272</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O219A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17591</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13161826</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13161826</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98196</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53272)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98196)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 431:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The first, last, or, The formal hypocrite further from salvation (as to the way of God's ordinary working) than the prophane sinner being the substance of several sermons preached in course at a lecture in the countrey / by J.O. ...</title>
                  <author>Oldfield, John, 1627?-1682.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 144 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Boulter ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1666.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Written by John Oldfield. Cf. DNB.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Salvation --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98196:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Firſt, Laſt.</p>
            <p>OR, The Formal Hypocrite further from Salvation, (as to the Way of God's ordinary working) than the Prophane Sinner.</p>
            <p>Being the Subſtance of ſeveral SERMONS Preached in Courſe at a LECTURE in the Countrey, By <hi>J. O.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Diſcourſe tending to draw the Prophane Sinner to God, by working on his Hopes; and to drive the Formaliſt out of his For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality, by working on his Fears.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Tim. 3.5.</hi>
               </bibl> Having a form of godlineſs, but denying the power thereof, from ſuch turn away.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Phil. 3.3.</hi>
               </bibl> For we are the circumſion, which worſhip God in the Spirit, and rejoyce in Chriſt Jeſus, and have no confidence in the fleſh.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Boulter,</hi> at the <hi>Turks-Head,</hi> in <hi>Cornhill.</hi> 1666.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:98196:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98196:2"/>
            <head>To the PARISHIONERS of <hi>C.</hi> and <hi>W.</hi> in the County of <hi>D.</hi> Grace and Peace from God the Father, and from our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</head>
            <p>IT is an undoubted Truth, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced by Truth it ſelf, <hi>That except a man be born again, he cannot ſee the Kingdom of God, Joh. 3.3.</hi> That Fleſh and Blood can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not inherit the Kingdom of God,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.50.</note> nor corruption incorruption. Such is the connexion betwixt Converſion and Salvation, Holineſs and Happineſs, That I may truly ſay, (yet not dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gating from the infinite worth of his Sufferings) that Chriſt cannot ſave an unconverted Soul; he ſaves none from Hell, but whom he ſaves from their ſins; nor will free-Grace it ſelf ſave a graceleſs perſon. It is therefore one main Piece of a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
<pb facs="tcp:98196:3"/>
imployment, (whoſe work is the ſalvation of ſouls) to endeavour the bringing of men from Self to Chriſt, from ſin to holineſs; to deal with them, as Ambaſſadors for Chriſt, as though God did beſeech them by us, even to pray them in Chriſts ſtead, that they will be recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil'd to God, <hi>2 Cor. 5.20.</hi> In order to this great End, nothing ſeems to me more effectually conducing, then the diſcovery and removal of thoſe things, which are the ordinary impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments of Converſion, amongſt which theſe two are very common.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> Some think they are paſt hope, they are in their own apprehenſions out of merci's reach; and therefore, either deſperately, or deſpairingly throw away their own ſouls.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> Others think they are paſt fear, that they are eſcaped the wrath to come; ſay, as <hi>Agag. 1 Sam. 15.32. Surely the bitterneſs of death is paſt;</hi> when, alas, they do but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb facs="tcp:98196:3"/>
themſelves with a vain ſhew, and are but in a cleaner way to Hell.</p>
            <p>The firſt of theſe is incident to groſs Sinners, when it pleaſes God to awaken their Conſciences, and cauſe a Dart of Conviction to ſtick in their hearts; Yea, the leaſt ſin diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, and ſet home to purpoſe on the ſoul, is apt to work this way: Nor can I think that thoſe Ranting, Roar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Deſperado's, who ſpend their days in Riot and Exceſs, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit all uncleanneſs with greedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, are altogether free from ſuch thoughts.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is the common <hi>Remora</hi> of the Formaliſt's Converſion, who flatters himſelf in his own eyes, till his iniquity be found hateful. Now to diſcover to the former, their grounds of hope, upon their Humble, Penitent return to God; and to the other, the cauſe they have to fear leaſt they be caſt off by God, ſeems the moſt
<pb facs="tcp:98196:4"/>
probable rational way to prevail with them, in order to their Converſion and Salvation.</p>
            <p>This was the Deſign of theſe poor Labours, when Preſented to your Ears from the Pulpit; and upon the ſame account are they now Preſented to your Eyes from the Preſs. If thou art <hi>(Reader)</hi> in either of theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, (and how great a part of the Chriſtian World will be found in the one or other of them!) here is ſomething in this ſmall Treatiſe, that may, by the bleſſing of him that teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to profit, be of uſe and advantage to thee. Or if thou be an Iſraelite in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, thou wilt find ſomething that may ſuit thy condition, and that may put thee upon more vigour and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity in Gods way.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not trouble you with any Apology, either for my ſelf or the Work; weakneſſes (the Lord knows) abound in both: Nor is it the deſign of this poor Labour to ſatisfie thy Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity,
<pb facs="tcp:98196:4"/>
or pleaſe thy Fancy, but (which is far higher) to profit and edifie thy Soul. That this may be the Fruit of it, is the hearty prayer of him, who deſires to be, and earneſtly beggs thy prayers that he may be</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A publike Helper on of thy Faith and happineſs, <hi>J. O.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:98196:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98196:5"/>
            <head>The Firſt, Last, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Matthew 21. latter part of 31. Verſe.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Verily I ſay unto you, That the Publicans and the Harlots go into the Kingdom of God before you.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> A Threefold uſe of Parables; the Text Divided and Explained; the Doctrine Propoſ'd and Proved by Scripture.</head>
               <p>PArables in Scipture are uſed eſpecially upon a Threefold account: Firſt, Judicially, to blind the eyes of thoſe who wilfully cloſe their eyes againſt the light, <hi>Mark</hi> 4.11, 12. Secondly, to Illuſtrate the Truth to thoſe that are willing to underſtand, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.12. <hi>If I have told you earthly things,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>i. e.</hi> Heavenly things
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98196:6"/>
illuſtrated by Earthly Parables and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblances. Thirdly, to blind men at firſt, that they may ſee better afterwards; or to make them own their ſin and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn themſelves unawares in a third perſon, which directly they would not do. Of this ſort is <hi>Nathan</hi>'s Parable to <hi>David,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. and many of Chriſt's Parables to the Jewes; two whereof we find in this Chapter. <hi>viz.</hi> That of the two Sons commanded to work in the Vineyard, <hi>verſ.</hi> 28, 33. and that of the Vineyard let out to the ingrateful Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandmen, <hi>verſ.</hi> 33.42. The Text in hand is the Reddition and Application of the former, wherein our Saviour wreſteth from the Prieſts and Elders (for to them eſpecially the Parable was ſpoken) a ſentence of condemnation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt themſelves,<note place="margin">Verſ. 23.</note> under the reſemblance of that Son, who ſaid, I go Sir, but went not. Yea, forceth them to judge the Publicans and ſinners (ſhadowed by the other Son) better and happier then them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: having brought them to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the Premiſes, in the Text he plainly laies down the Concluſion.</p>
               <p>The words are an Aſſertion; in which obſerve,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:98196:6"/>1. The Aſſertor; Jeſus Chriſt, who was Truth it ſelf.</item>
                  <item>2. The note of Aſſertion, or Aſſercra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; Verily,</item>
                  <item>3. The Aſſertion it ſelf; wherein there is obſervable,
<list>
                        <item>1. A Collation, or compariſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Prieſts and Elders, and the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licans and ſinners.</item>
                        <item>2. A Praelation, or preferring the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter before the former.</item>
                        <item>3. The thing wherein they are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, <hi>viz.</hi> their greater readineſs to embrace the Goſpel, and to go into the Kingdom of God.— A little for expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>[Publicans and Harlots]</hi> are here Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nechdochically put for the worſt of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; for ſo they were deſervedly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed.</p>
               <p>Publicans were Officers belonging to the <hi>Romans,</hi> (though, for the moſt part, Jews by Nation) not much unlike our Exciſe-men, or Tole-gatherers; amongſt whom, ſome were, as it were, Farmers, (ſuch I ſuppoſe was <hi>Zacheus, Luke</hi> 19.2.) Others of an inferiour Rank, Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors: both given to Rapine, Oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Injuſtice, Violence, and were the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98196:7"/>
                  <hi>Romans</hi> chief inſtruments to grind the faces of their poor Brethren: hereby contracting upon them the juſt odium of the Jewiſh Nation. Hence that ſuitable counſel of <hi>John</hi> to them, <hi>Luk.</hi> 3.13. <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act no more then that which is appointed you.</hi> Upon this account <hi>Zacheus</hi> (as a ſpecial teſtimony of his ſincere repentance) of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers a fourfold reſtitution of any thing got by falſe accuſation, <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.8. That being the ſin of his calling. Yea ſo wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed they were, that in Scripture, Heathen and Publican are equivalent, <hi>Mat</hi> 18.17. So that when our Saviour would beat the Jews out of their carnal confidences, and high conceits of themſelves and their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, he ordinarily compares them with Publicans, ſhewing them, that they either come up no higher then they, as <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.46, 47. or, that they fall ſhort of them, as <hi>Luke</hi> 18.10-14. and this Text. Yea, ſo wicked were they thought, that it was judg'd a crime in our Saviour to converſe with them, <hi>Matth.</hi> 9.11. and caſt upon him, as a grand opprobrium, that he was a friend of Publicans and ſinners, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.9.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Harlots</hi> (their ſin is too well known amongſt us) <hi>Gr.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Vendor:</hi>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:98196:7"/>
properly thoſe, <hi>quae corpus habent venale,</hi> who proſtitute their bodies for money. If you would ſee their wickedneſs, read <hi>Proverbs</hi> 6, and 7. Chapters, and 23, 27, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Some think that 27. Chapter to be Allegorical, and that under the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of an Harlot, is repreſented the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful and deſtructive nature of ſin: if ſo, this ſin is exceeding ſinful, which (though but one ſpecies) yet contains in it the whole nature and properties of its genus; and is, as it were, an Epitome of all ſin.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>[Kingdom of God]</hi> is uſed in many ſenſes; to paſs by other, it is taken ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times for the ſtate of Grace, the Church Militant; ſometimes for the ſtate of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, or Church Triumphant: here both may be taken in, the one as the Way, the other as the End. So that the plain ſenſe is, Publicans and Harlots, notorious vile ſinners, ſooner repent, believe, embrace the Goſpel, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo conſequently come to Heaven, then you formal, ſelf-conceited Jews, Prieſts and Elders.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>[Before you]</hi> The ſpeech is ſomething improper, (as <hi>Beza</hi> notes) <hi>Improprie hîc dicuntur praeire, quos nemo ſequitur.</hi> They go before you; <hi>i. e.</hi> they are ſaved, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98196:8"/>
you periſh; as appears by comparing this with <hi>Matth.</hi> 8.11, 12. <hi>The children of the Kingdom ſhall be caſt out into outer darkneſs.</hi> They upon Faith and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance are made happy in glory, while you continuing in unbelief and impenitency fall into eternal perdition.</p>
               <p>The words thus opened, take the ſenſe of them in this plain Doctrinal Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or Concluſion.</p>
               <p>Doctr. <hi>That the vileſt ſinners, Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans and Harlots,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>often believe, repent and are ſaved, while Phariſaical, ſelf-juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying Formaliſts continue in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief and Impenitency, and ſo periſh eternally.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Proof.</hi> Thus you ſee it was in the courſe of <hi>John</hi>'s preaching, <hi>verſ.</hi> 31. and thus it fell out in our Saviours preaching. <hi>Levi</hi> the Publican becomes <hi>Matthew</hi> the Evangeliſt, <hi>Luke</hi> 5.27. with <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.3. <hi>Zacheus</hi> the chief of the Publicans, and very rich, becomes a Son of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham; i. e.</hi> a Penitent believer: <hi>Luke</hi> 19.9. <hi>Magdalen</hi> the Harlot, is made <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalen</hi> the Convert, <hi>Luke</hi> 7.37.—Nor was it onely ſo with theſe two or three; but, <hi>Mark</hi> 2.15. Many Publicans and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98196:8"/>
ſinners followed him, <hi>Luke</hi> 7.29, 30. <hi>The Publicans juſtified God— But the Phariſees and Lawyers rejected the counſel of God againſt themſelves,</hi> &amp;c. Nay, <hi>Luke</hi> 15.12. <hi>Then drew near unto him all the Publicans and Sinners for to hear him, and the Phariſees and Scribes murmured</hi>— A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt theſe ſelf-conceited, ſelf-juſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Formaliſts, there was but <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nus &amp; alter,</hi> one <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> one <hi>Joſeph,</hi> one <hi>Paul;</hi> and not many more that I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member. That queſtion, <hi>John</hi> 7.48. <hi>Have any of the Rulers or of the Phariſees believed on him?</hi> implies the rarity of ſuch mens coming in. So that as it is ſaid of Miniſters, <hi>Quis unquam vidit Cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ricum paenitentem;</hi> (though I hope ſuch are no black Swans in this age) ſo it might have been ſaid in that age, <hi>Quis unquam vidit Phariſaeum paenitentem?</hi> Who ever ſaw a Phariſee, a Scribe, a Ruler, a Lawyer repenting? Nor was it otherwiſe in the Apoſtles time; (the immediate Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of Chriſt) you will find through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Hiſtory of the <hi>Acts,</hi> that the formal Jews were the greateſt contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the Apoſtles Doctrine, and the moſt deadly inveterate haters and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors of their perſons; while whole
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98196:9"/>
Cities and Countries of the prophane Idolatrous Gentiles, readily embrace, ſteadfaſtly believe, and cordially obey their Goſpel. Take a few inſtances a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong many, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.5.— <hi>Philip</hi> hath incredible ſucceſs in <hi>Samaria,</hi> the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel is received there with great joy, <hi>v.</hi> 8. which the Jews had driven away from them by a great perſecution, <hi>verſ.</hi> 1. So <hi>Acts</hi> 13.45. <hi>The Jews ſeeing the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes, are filled with envy—contradict, blaſpheme;</hi> but <hi>verſ.</hi> 48. <hi>The Gentiles are glad, and glorifie the word of the Lord, and as many as were ordained to eternal life, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved;</hi> whereas the Jews, <hi>v.</hi> 50. do, <hi>Omnem moverê lapidem, ſtir up the devout and honorable women, and the chief men of the City, and raiſed perſecution againſt Paul and Barnabas, and expelled them out of their Coaſts.</hi> Go to the 14 Chapter, at <hi>Iconium</hi> a great multitude both of Jews and Greeks beleeved, <hi>v.</hi> 1. But then, <hi>v.</hi> 2. the unbelieving Jews ſtirred up the Gentiles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> — At <hi>Lyſtra,</hi> the Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous people miſtaking the Apoſtles, for their ſuppoſed Heatheniſh Deities, are ſcarce reſtrained from doing ſacrifice unto them. Here was a wide door open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and might in all probability have
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98196:9"/>
proved more effectual, had not the inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate enemies of the Goſpel, the carnal Jews, ſtopt the paſſage by enraging the people againſt the Apoſtles, as you may ſee, <hi>v.</hi> 19. Go on to the 17. Chapter, <hi>v.</hi> 1.5.— You find the Apoſtles ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully preaching the Goſpel at <hi>Theſſaloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca,</hi> a great multitude of devout Greeks believing, <hi>and of the chief women not a few, v.</hi> 4. But <hi>v.</hi> 5. the Jews their old ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries oppoſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The like ſucceſs they had at <hi>Berea, v.</hi> 10, 11, 12. and the ſame oppoſers, <hi>v.</hi> 13. At <hi>Corinth, Acts</hi> 18.8. with 12, 13. At <hi>Rome,</hi> though few of the Jews believed, <hi>Acts</hi> 28.23.— to the end; yet the ſeed which <hi>Paul</hi> caſt there, ſprung up into a flouriſhing Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile-Church, whoſe Faith was ſpoken of throughout the whole World, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.8. 'Tis needleſs to heap up inſtances of this nature, they being common and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious to any that obſerve them. Thus you ſee that <hi>de facto</hi> it was ſo; (and the caſe is not much alter'd now) that it was much more ordinary and frequent, to ſee a penitent Publican or Harlot, or the like groſs Sinner, then to ſee a proud, ſelf-juſtifying Phariſee, or Formaliſt, repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and embracing Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:98196:10"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> A firſt ſort of Reaſons, (<hi>viz.</hi> What may move God to call the Prophane, rather then the Formaliſts) Negatively, and Poſitively.</head>
               <p>NOw it will be well worthy of our pains, to enquire into the Reaſon of this evident Truth; and thoſe may be two wayes conſidered.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Quoad Deum,</hi> in reference to God, what may move God rather to call Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licans and Harlots, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then Self-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited Formaliſts?</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Quoad media ſalutis,</hi> in reference to the means of Salvation: Why the Preaching of the Goſpel ſhould more frequently and kindly operate upon Publicans and Harlots, (ſeemingly the moſt uncapable ſubjects) then upon Morally Righteous, and ſeemingly holy perſons; who may ſeem more then half<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hew'd and ſquared, even ready to be lai'd into the building of the Church?</p>
               <p>Concerning the firſt ſort of Reaſons, it is not alwaies ſafe, I confeſs, to enquire into the ſecrets of the Almighty; I ſhall therefore endeavour according to the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98196:10"/>
Apoſtles Rule, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.3. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; To be wiſe unto ſobriety: Nor ſhall I enter any further into this Laby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth then I am guided by the thread of Scripture; ſomething I ſhall hint nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, and ſomething affirmatively.</p>
               <p n="1">I. Negatively: And firſt, It is not from any want of Power in God to make the means of Grace effectual to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of one as well as another, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.14. Is any thing too hard for the Lord? Suppoſe the Converſion of a Formaliſt a work of more difficulty then of a Profane Sinner; yet to Infinite Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer all things are alike feiſable; to Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Wiſdom all miſteries alike diſcerna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, to Infinite Mercy all Sins alike Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable.</p>
               <p>Nor, Secondly, is it to to be ſuppoſed, that there is more of merit in the one, then in the other, to induce God to call the one, and paſs by the other: Nay, if this might carry it, we ſhould rather i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine that the moral, formal perſon ſhould be called, and the profane caſt off: The former being (at leaſt in appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance) like Stone or Timber, almoſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for the Building; the other like
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98196:11"/>
crooked, knotty Timber<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or rugged Stones, which require abundance of pains in hewing and ſquaring, before they can be fitted for God's uſe: ſo that if merit, or that congruous, praevious diſpoſition which the Papiſts dream of, were any inducement to move God; then it's like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Formaliſt, and civilly righteous Perſon, ſhould be the firſt in God's Eye; But the Truth is, God orders it other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, that it may appear, <hi>That it is not in him that willeth, nor in him that run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 9.10</note>And then, Thirdly, Leaſt of all is it to be imagined, that God calleth the Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can, Harlot, or other Profane Sinner, as having any greater delight in them as ſuch: No ſurely, ſin is the ſole object of God's hatred; <hi>Hab.</hi> 1.13. <hi>He is of purer eyes then to behold iniquity.</hi> And for Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licans and Harlots, whom doth God more abhor? <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.1-5. <hi>Oppreſſion, and grinding the Faces of the Poor</hi> (which was the Publicans ſin) <hi>cries in Gods Ears.</hi> And <hi>Habbak.</hi> 2.11, 12. <hi>The Stone ſhall cry out of the Wall, &amp;c.</hi> and for Harlots, ſee <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.4. <hi>Whoremongers and Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers God will judg;</hi> Far be it from us, to think that God therefore calleth ſuch,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98196:11"/>
becauſe he takes complacency in them as ſuch: No, when they are called, they muſt come home by weeping Croſs; they muſt cleanſe their hands, and puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie their hearts, before they can have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Communion with the unſpotted Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of Heaven. This <hi>Negatively.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Affirmatively,</hi> to make it evident to all the World, that he is no reſpecter of perſons; that there is nothing out of himſelf, which is the leaſt inducement to him to call one, or reject another. Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly:</p>
               <p n="1">1. To depreſs Man's Merit, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.26-30. <hi>Not many wiſe men after the fleſh, &amp;c. are called; but God hath choſen the fooliſh things of the World to confound the wiſe, &amp;c.</hi> And why ſo? The reaſon is rendred, <hi>v.</hi> 29. <hi>That no fleſh ſhould glory in his preſence.</hi> God's deſign is, to exclude man's boaſting, <hi>Rom</hi> 3.27. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.9. And what more effectual way to do it then this?</p>
               <p n="2">2. To exalt his own Mercy, (a neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry conſequent of the former) Man's Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and God's Mercy being like a pair of Scales or Buckets, as the one riſes, the other falls. This you ſee, <hi>Jer.</hi> 9.23. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.15. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.7. When thoſe are called,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98196:12"/>
juſtified, ſanctified and ſaved, who were the vileſt and baſeſt of men, the greateſt of ſinners; and in the mean while, others of high Parts, moral Accompliſhments, of much ſeeming Sanctity, rejected. Oh, what admiring thoughts muſt ſuch needs have to all eternity, of the freeneſs of God's Mercy! See 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.12,-16. This will fill their mouths with the High Praiſes of the moſt High God, and make them ſtrive to raiſe their hearts to the higheſt pitch of Thankfulneſs. Thus much for the Reaſons reſpecting God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> A ſecond ſort of Reaſons (<hi>viz.</hi> Why the Word ſooner works on the Prophane, then the Formaliſt) in general.</head>
               <p n="2">2. BUt that which more concerns us to enquire into, is, Why the means of Salvation hath an eaſier in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence upon, and finds readier accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with the Publican and Harlot, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then with the Formaliſt and hypocritical Profeſſor? For ſince God ordinarily works by means, and that means ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily hath more or leſs operation, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98196:12"/>
to the greater capacity, or incapaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the ſubject it meets with; why ſhould not the Word rather find enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment into the hearts of the Moral For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal perſon, then the Prophane Sinner?</p>
               <p>In general take this account of it; There are more obſtructions and impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments lye in the way of the Goſpel, to hinder its work upon the Formaliſt, then upon the Prophane: though in reſpect of God's abſolute power it is alike eaſie; yet in reſpect of his ordinary way of working, it is more difficult to convert the former than the later: And theſe Obſtructions, are either, 1. <hi>Ab intrâ:</hi> or, 2. <hi>Ab extrâ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sect. 1. <hi>Inward Impediments of the words effect upon the Formaliſt,</hi> viz. <hi>ſuch as are in himſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Ab intrâ.</hi> There are many things in the Formaliſt himſelf to hinder his Converſion, which are not found in the Prophane.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reaſon</hi> 1. It is much more difficult to convince a Formaliſt of Sin, (which is a neceſſary Anticedent to Converſion) then a Prophane perſon; and this I make out by a twofold conſideration.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is evident that man, every man, is
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98196:13"/>
naturally averſe to Conviction: Like an old Thief, that will ſtand it out as long as he can, will juſtifie himſelf, and plead, Not guilty. Sin and Shifting came into the world together. <hi>Adam</hi> laies the fault upon his Wife, ſhe upon the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.11, 12, 13. Thus the Jews deal with God, they put him to prove, <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.23, 29, 35. and ſtand upon their own juſtification. So often in <hi>Malachi,</hi> Chap. 1.7. and 2.13, 14, 17. and 3.7, 8, 13. <hi>Wherein have we polluted thee? And wherein have we robbed thee? And what have we ſpoken ſo much againſt thee?</hi> They will not own their ſin and ſhame. Man is loath to ſee and own his fault; 'tis death to him to be found guilty; as <hi>Job</hi> 24.15, 17. <hi>The eye of the Adulterer waiteth for the twilight,— If one know them, they are in the terrors of the ſhadow of death:</hi> till we deal with them, as <hi>Tamar</hi> with her Father in Law, <hi>Judah, Gen.</hi> 38.25. <hi>Produce the Signet Bracelets and Staff;</hi> undeniable teſtimonies of their guilt, Sinners will not be convinced. How will they deny, elude, excuſe, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenuate, and as <hi>Michol,</hi> lay an Image in the Bed that <hi>David</hi> may eſcape? cloak their ſin with the name of vertue, that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98196:13"/>
the Hue and Cry of the Word may not find it out? A Fig-leaf rather then no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhall cover their nakedneſs. 'Tis diſcernable in the beſt, <hi>David</hi> owns not his ſin, till it be directly charg'd upon him, <hi>Thou art the man,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.7. <hi>Aſa</hi> (though a good man, 2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 4.2.) is wroth with the Seer,<note place="margin">2 Ch. 16.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> puts him in a priſon-houſe, and is in a rage with him, becauſe of his plain and home reproof. Man, like a ſtout enemy, will not yield ſo long as he hath any Fortreſs to fly to. And then</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Formaliſt hath more ſhifts and evaſions, then the prophane Sinner; he hath more to ſay for himſelf, more excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and pretences to cloak his ſin withal: as ſome wild Beaſts have many Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, or Shelters to fly to when purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; <hi>Achan</hi> confeſſes not, till his very perſon be taken. Though the Tribe be taken, yet poſſibly the Lot may fall upon another Family; the Family is taken, but perhaps his Houſhold may eſcape; his Houſhold is taken, yet it may be the Lot may light upon ſome other perſon; while there is any hope, <hi>Achan</hi> yields not. Thus it is with the Formaliſt, many things lie betwixt him and the Word; he
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98196:14"/>
hath a very thick covering; whereas the prophane perſon lies more open and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked before the Word. Some of theſe ſhifts I ſhall mention, to which it will be eaſie to add many more.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Letter of the Law juſties him in a great meaſure, whereas it condemns the profane perſon: He looks upon the bare letter and ſhell of the Law, and is ready to ſay as he <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.20. <hi>All theſe things have I obſerved from my youth:</hi> Thus the Jews, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.17. Thou art called a Jew, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, reſteſt in or upon the Law: and <hi>v.</hi> 23. Thou ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt thy boaſt of the Law, <hi>(i.e.)</hi> as being an exact obſerver of it, and ſo expecting to be juſtified by it. So it was with <hi>Paul,</hi> while a Phariſee, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.6. as touching the righteouſneſs of the Law, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, blameleſs, without fault, no juſt charge or complaint could be brought againſt him, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9, 10, 11. The Law is not made for (the condemnation of) the Righteous, but for the Lawleſs and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient; for the Ungodly, and Sinners; for unholy, and Profane; for Murderers of Fathers, and Murderers of Mothers; for Man-ſlayers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Formaliſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes, But I am no ſuch perſon, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98196:14"/>
therefore concludes, that the Law con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns him not. 'Tis true, <hi>in Theſi,</hi> men will eaſily acknowledg that the Law is comprehenſive, that more is included in it then is expreſſed; But bring it down <hi>ad Hypotheſin,</hi> to their particular caſes and ſins, and then they will ſcarce ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg any thing a Duty but what is expreſly commanded; or a Sin, but what is expreſly forbidden. The Jews had a Proverbial Speech, That upon every a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pex or tittle of Scripture did hang a mountain of ſenſe; yet in point of pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, or conviction, or confeſſion of ſin, little or nothing is owned as a duty or ſin, but what hath the expreſs injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction or inhibition of the Word: See it in the example of the ſelf-juſtifying Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſee, <hi>Luke</hi> 18.11. He mentions no ſins but ſuch as the very letter of the Law condemns; Extortioners Unjuſt, Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as if, becauſe he was none of thoſe groſſer ſinners, therefore he was no ſinner at all. 'Tis evident alſo by that narrow gloſs which the Jewiſh Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bies had put upon ſeveral of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, refelled by our Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.21. And thus it is with a formal Profeſſor of the Goſpel; and becauſe he
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98196:15"/>
finds not himſelf guilty of thoſe groſſer ſins condemned by the letter of the Law, and light of Nature, he declines the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing, humbling power of the Word, and ſhrowds himſelf from it under this ſhelter, whereas the Profane Perſon, the Common Drunkard, Adulterer, Swea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> lies naked before the very letter of the Law, and every blow is upon the bare.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As the Letter of the Law, ſo natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Conſcience acquits him, and ſpeaks peace to him. 'Tis dim-ſighted, and, till illightned by the Spirit of God, takes no notice of motes, ſmaller ſins: and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al it is (while natural) corrupt and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial; juſtifying, when it ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn. 'Tis like an ignorant and unjuſt Judg, who either, through blindneſs can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, or bribery will not, take cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance of the Malefactors crime. Now this is requiſite in order to conviction of ſin, that Conſcience ſee and own, and charge it upon the ſinner. 'Tis not all the witneſs from without, that will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince a man, till Conſcience do <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, join its Teſtimony, and charge the crime home upon the man. Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, whether its Teſtimony be true,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98196:15"/>
or falſe, is <hi>Mutus Ahaeneus,</hi> a Brazen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wall to fence off Conviction: What will a man care though all the World accuſe him, while Conſcience acquits him? And thus it is with a Formaliſt, his Conſcience is an eaſie Judg, like that Steward, <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.6. willing to take up with duty to the halves, Fifty for an hundred; and not finding him guilty of groſſer ſins, paſſeth a ſentence of Abſolution upon him; and being thus fortified, he can eaſily outface the word of Miniſters, and withſtand all attempts made upon him for his Convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. Now with groſs ſinners it is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe; even natural Conſcience bears witneſs againſt him; even Heathen's Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences accuſe for ſins againſt the light of Nature, and thoſe impreſſions of the Law of God which remain upon their hearts: See <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.14, 15. Natural Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience takes little notice of Habits, but when they break out into groſs Acts, as Murther, Adultery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> here, it cannot be altogether ſilent. Moſt profane Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners are (as 'tis ſaid of a convinced He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.11.) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condemned perſons, and therefore it is ordinarily much more eaſie to convince them of a ſin, when we have the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:98196:16"/>
of a witneſs in their boſoms to join with us: 'Tis the proper office of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to witneſs with, or againſt a man, to acquit, or condemn him (in ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination to God's Word:) But having in a great meaſure, loſt both its know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg and honeſty (the two eſſential re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſites in a Judg) by the fall, it will not accuſe, except the crime be palpable and undeniable, unleſs the ſin carry a dreadful aſpect, and have diſobedience written in the very forehead of it; Till the beams of the Sun of Righteouſneſs be darted in, the Formaliſt's motes lie undiſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and his blind and partial Conſcience gives an abſolving Verdict.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Another ſhrowd or ſhelter, under which the Formaliſt lurks, and by which he declines the convincing power of the Word, is the ſecrecy of his ſins: He thinks he dances in a Net, and acts un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen. So that though the Arrow of the Word be directed to his Breaſt and hits his ſin, yet he perſwades himſelf it was not intended; though Conſcience ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times owns the ſin, being ſtruck at by the Word, and begins to charge it upon him, yet he ſoon ſtops its mouth, by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading himſelf, that the Miniſter did but
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:98196:16"/>
accidentally light upon it, that it was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended againſt ſome other perſon: whereas the prophane perſon, being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcious of the notoriouſneſs of his ſins, and that they are ſuch as are obvious to the worlds eye, he is ready to think that every word is directed to him; and therefore more apt to apply it. The Formaliſt, though conſcious of a ſin re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, yet is ready to think, who ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines that I am guilty of ſuch a ſin? I paſs for a godly man, a ſincere Chriſtian, in the opinion of good men; my Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, I know, judges better, and hath o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thoughts of me; and thus he waves the Charge. A ſtout Thief will ſtand upon his own juſtification, and outface the Judg, when he knows the Act was ſo ſecret that there can be no Teſtimony produced; thus it is with a Formaliſt, whoſe ſins for the moſt part, are Chamber-ſins, Cloſet-ſins, ſuch as are out of mens cognizance. The notoriouſneſs of a ſin, is many times a help to conviction. It's an eaſier matter to make a Malefactor own, and confeſs that crime, whereof he knows an hundred Witneſſes may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, then of that which he preſumes is known to none but himſelf. I may uſe
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98196:17"/>
that (at leaſt elluſively) to this purpoſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.24. <hi>If one come in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth not, or is unlearned, he is convinc'd of all, he is judg'd of all:</hi> So the notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly prophane perſon, when his drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enneſs, uncleanneſs, ſwearing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are ſpoke to, he is ready to think, this is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended againſt me, and that every one in the Congregation, will interpret it as ſpoken to him; and though it is true, that ſometimes this heightens his hatred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Word and Miniſter, yet if God ſet in with it, it hath a contrary opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>viz.</hi> to edge the Word, and faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litate conviction.</p>
               <p n="4">4. (VVhich is of affinity to all the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) The ſmallneſs of his ſin, is another ſhelter; they are not aggravated by thoſe bloody and heightning circumſtances, as the ſins of others. He baptizeth them with the name of ſlips, infirmities, ſins of dayly incurſion, unavoidable weakneſſes, ſpots of God's own Children, ſuch as are incident and common to the beſt of men; nothing befalls him, in this, but what is ordinary; yea, he compares his ſins with thoſe of the godly, recorded in Scripture; <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Lying; <hi>Noah</hi>'s Drunkenneſs; <hi>Lot</hi>'s Inceſt; <hi>David</hi>'s
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:98196:17"/>
Murther and Adultery; <hi>Peter</hi>'s Denying and Forſwearing his Maſter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And finding his ſins to fall very much ſhort, in point of guilt and ſcandal, he not only concludes his condition good and ſafe, but applauds himſelf as a Chriſtian of a high form, and great attainments. Now while a man judges thus of himſelf, it is impoſſible to faſten any humbling con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction upon him. 'Tis neceſſary, in order to conviction, that a man not only ſee ſin, but ſee its ſinfulneſs, hainouſneſs, and aggravated by its circumſtances, till a man ſay, as <hi>David, Pſalm</hi> 25.11. <hi>Pardon my ſin, for it is great;</hi> till with <hi>Paul,</hi> he apprehend it, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Rom,</hi> 7.13. <hi>Out of meaſure ſinful;</hi> till he look upon himſelf as the chief of ſinners, he will not be to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe convinced, or humbled. Then will he cry out with <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 7.14. <hi>I am carnal, ſold under ſin.</hi> 'Tis ſin, clothed with exaggerated circumſtances of Guilt, Scandal, Rebellion, Atheiſm, Contempt of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that awakens the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and faſtens the Dart of conviction in the heart of a ſinner. I acknowledg indeed, that the ſame light is requiſite to diſcover the hainouſneſs of a prophane
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:98196:18"/>
perſons ſin, and the Arrow muſt be ſhot with the ſame Hand, out of the ſame Bow, that pricks and pierces his heart, (for we ſee, that even thoſe groſſer ſins of drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enneſs, adultery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are by many counted venial infirmities, tricks of youth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) yet if we conſider the means, whereby God ordinarily works on men, it will appear, that where ſins are greater, more palpable, more directly againſt the expreſs Letter of the word, it is an eaſier thing to bring the ſinner to acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and conviction; ſince, in ſuch caſes, the Law and Conſcience will bear wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs againſt the ſinner. That ſin, the very act and matter whereof is expreſly condemned by the word, is more eaſily ſet home upon a man, then when onely ſome circumſtance makes it to be a ſin: Yet on the other hand, I acknowledg, that the ſmalleſt ſin, aggravated upon the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience by the Spirit of God, (whoſe work it is to convince of ſin, <hi>John</hi> 16.8.) will appear exceeding ſinful.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bolton</hi>'s Soul-ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation, <hi>p.</hi> 118.</note> 
                  <hi>Auguſtines</hi> robbing an Orchard, when a Youth, was afterwards a ſin very hainous in his eyes, when he conſidered it in its circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; and he aggravates it upon himſelf, by conſidering that it was againſt the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98196:18"/>
very light of Nature; that he did it with a full propenſity of will; not for want, but wantonneſs, having better fruit of his own; not ſo much out of love to the Fruit, as out of love to Sin; that he joyned himſelf with wicked company, did it at Midnight, having ſpent the time before in Luxury and Vanity; that they carried away great Burdens; when they came home, they had no ſuch deſire to eat them, but caſt them to the Swine. Upon theſe and the like conſiderations, he breaks out into a paſſionate indignation againſt himſelf, and exclamation, to God; <hi>Behold my heart, O my God, behold my heart, which thou haſt pitied in the loweſt Hell.</hi> Thus a ſmall ſin, ſeen in Gods light, appears odious and exceeding hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous: Even thoſe, <hi>Motus primo primi,</hi> (as the Schools call them) the ſuddain and indeliberate ſuggeſtions of ſin, not coming up to conſent, or action, have been mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſtrong conviction and deep humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation to ſome ſouls; yea and have more affected them, then the groſſeſt acts, and greateſt exorbitancies: Yet if we look at God's ordinary way of working, which is by the VVord and Conſcience, it will be eaſie to conceive, that a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:98196:19"/>
ſcandalous ſinner, is in a nearer capacity of conviction; then he whoſe ſins are but as Motes to the others Beams, as Mole-hills to the others Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The laſt refuge I ſhall mention, is the ſeeming Graces he hath, and the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties he doth. Many good things are found in him, and proceed from him; theſe he ballanceth with his ſins, and find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Sins ſmall, his Graces (as he ſuppoſes) ſtrong and vigorous, his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances many and excellent, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes well of himſelf; and under this thick Covering, he ſhrouds himſelf from the power of the VVord; behind this Bulwark he ſecures himſelf from the Gun-ſhot of Conviction. Thus the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſee, <hi>Luke</hi> 18.11, 12. <hi>I am not as other men are, Extortioners, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt, Adulterers, nor even as this Publican:</hi> Here you ſee he looks upon himſelf, as free from great enormities; then <hi>v.</hi> 12. <hi>I Faſt twice in the week, I give tythes of all that I poſſeſs:</hi> Here's his more then ordinary piety towards God; he is twice a week in a duty of an extraordinary nature; and here's his more then common equity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man; he payes Tythes of all, even
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:98196:19"/>
thoſe things which the Law had leſt doubtful. Oh what magnifying and ſelf-applauding thoughts may we imagine him to have! How hardly could a man have faſtned any humbling, convincing word upon him? Thus it is with the Formaliſt, he looks upon his Zeal, Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Love to God, and other like Graces; (for ſo they appear to him, though indeed but common at beſt) then conſiders his Piety towards God, in his conſtancy in ordinary, and frequency in extraordinary Duties; his Equity and Mercy towards man; his Sobriety to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards himſelf; and finding himſelf, Rich,<note place="margin">Rev. 3.17.</note> and Full, and encreaſed with Goods, he thinks highly of himſelf, and admires himſelf, as much above the pitch of ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Chriſtians. Now being thus lifted up, it's no eaſie matter to bring him down; charge him with any ſin, he will weigh it down with many good duties: His courſe and the tenour of his life is for God and Holineſs, and thoſe ſins are but ſuch ſlips as the beſt are guilty of, in their journeying towards the heavenly <hi>Canaan</hi> Now with the Prophane per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon 'tis otherwiſe, he hath no ſuch <hi>Aſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum;</hi> you take him Naked, and ſo the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:98196:20"/>
Dart will more eaſily hit, and pierce deeper. Thus you ſee the Formaliſt hath more Evaſions, Refuges, Fortificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons againſt conviction, then the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, and conſequently more difficult to convince him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reaſon</hi> 2. As it is harder to convince him of ſin, ſo to beat him out of Self; which yet muſt be done, or elſe a man is no true Convett; Self-denyal, is the firſt Leſſon we are taught in Chriſt's School; 'tis the A, B, C, of Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and eſpecially in point of juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to diſclaim our own Righteouſneſs, and caſt our ſelves, venture our hopes upon Chriſt and his Righteouſneſs, is the very <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> of a Chriſtian, and that which gives him, both the Name and thing. This is <hi>Paul</hi>'s frame, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.7, 11. he quits all for Chriſt. Now its no eaſie matter to bring a man to this; but eſpecially the Formaliſt is hardly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to it. He that thinks he hath ſomething, yea enough of his own, will not eaſily be perſwaded to go a Begging to anothers Door. Man is a proud creature, and loath to be beholding to any, till meer neceſſity force him: A Prodigal that hath waſted his Patrimony,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:98196:20"/>
and rioted away his eſtate, yet would fain appear as good a Man as his Father, and maintain the Garb and Cuſtom of his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors; while he hath any thing left, he will not let his povertie appear: Thus we; Our firſt Parents had a Stock of Righteouſneſs, though they prodigally ſpent it, and beggard themſelves and all their poſterity; yet we are loath to go a begging, till neceſſity wear out ſhame, and whip us out of our pride. Now the Formaliſt conceits, he hath a ſtock with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in himſelf to live upon; he can ſpin a VVeb out of his own Bowels to cover himſelf withal; and if he have but a Rag of his own, he values it above Silks of anothers giving; Home-ſpun cloath is better then the coſtlieſt cloath of Gold or Slver, of anothers providing. This is the great Impediment to a Formaliſt's converſion; how hard is it to perſwade him, that his ſeeming ſomething, is really nothing! 'Tis not the Precellency of Chriſts Righteouſneſs to ours, but a ſenſe of our abſolute need of his Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, that drives to Chriſt. There is a more direct oppoſition betwixt Self and Chriſt, then betwixt ſin and Chriſt; for ſin doth (at leaſt accidentally) drive us
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:98196:21"/>
unto Chriſt, but Self doth altogether draw us from Criſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.3. <hi>Going about to eſtabliſh their own righteouſneſs, they have not ſubmitted to the righteouſneſs of God:</hi> Setting up Self, is the pulling down of Chriſt. He is nothing to that man, that is any thing to himſelf; fleſh and blood taught not <hi>Paul</hi> that Leſſon, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.7,-11. As many Prayers, Faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Alms-deeds, good VVorks, or ſeeming Graces, as the Formaliſt hath, ſo many Bulwarks againſt conviction, and Arguments to diſſwade him from a cloſe with Chriſt. Now the Prophane perſon is an abſolute Bankrupt, an arrant Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, one that hath not ſo much as Husks of Duty (that I may allude to it) to fill his Belly, or ſatisfie his conſcience. He will be ready to cry out with the Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can, <hi>Lord be merciful to me a ſinner, Luke</hi> 18.13. while the Formaliſt (Phariſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like) is at his, <hi>God I thank thee,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>I faſt, I pay Tythes.</hi> I, and I ſtill; Self is mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified in all. Now is it not eaſier to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade a Beggar to ask an Alms, then one that is Rich, encreaſed with goods, and needs nothing? He that is ſtark naked, will ſooner be perſwaded to put on cloaths of anothers Free-gift, then he that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:98196:21"/>
is cloathed, and warm to his own appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reaſon</hi> 3. As the Formaliſt is more hardly beaten out of ſelf, ſo he is more difficultly perſwaded of his unregenerate eſtate, then the profane Perſon. He that thinks his eſtate good enough already, will not eaſily be perſwaded to change it: It's one ſtep to Converſion, to ſee our ſelves unconverted; to Happineſs, to ſee our ſelves miſerable. 'Tis <hi>Seneca</hi>'s expreſſion, <hi>Ideo mutari nolumus quia nos optimos eſſe credimus;</hi> The great reaſon of our perſiſting in our preſent condition, is, becauſe we conceit it good and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py. This conceit damps all. While men think their Priſon a Palace, they will not come out of it. Hereticks are confidently perſwaded they are in the right, and therefore their ears are ſtopt againſt means of reducement. True, the profaneſt think thus of themſelves, but they have no ground, and therefore are ſooner beaten out of this hold; but the Formaliſt hath much to ſay for himſelf, can produce many evidences, whereby he deceives himſelf and others. What Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are peculiar to a Chriſtian which he hath not in appearance, and in his own
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:98196:22"/>
apprehenſion? He loves God, Chriſt, the Word, Ordinances, the Brethren, yea, his Enemies; he hath Faith, Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, Zeal, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yea, he can remember the time when it was otherwiſe with him; he experienceth a real change in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; he hates where he loved, and loves where he hated. Now here is a double work to do; we muſt firſt raze thoſe falſe foundations, walls as high as Heaven; confute his reaſonings and arguments, which he produceth to prove his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, before we can faſten any thing upon him to draw him to Chriſt; and how hardly this will be done, is eaſie to imagine: Will a man be eaſily perſwaded to pull all down, and begin upon a new Foundation, when he hath brought it to the finiſhing? Will one that is at his journeys end, be drawn to begin it again? Can you prevail with a man that thinks himſelf at Heavens door, to return again by the gates of Hell? He that feels him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf well, and is, to his own apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſtrong and healthful, finds a univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Eucraſie; head and ſtomack, and each other part in its due temperament, will be hardly perſwaded that a mortal diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe hath ſeiſed upon him, or to take
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:98196:22"/>
Phyſick as one lying at the point of death. Men are not eaſily perſwaded out of an opinion of the goodneſs of their condition, when they ſeem to have taken it upon warrantable grounds.</p>
               <q>Prona venit cupidis in ſua vota fides.</q>
               <p>Men are eaſily perſwaded to believe that which they would have to be; and as hardly diſſwaded from believing it. Now a profane perſon hath no ſuch evidences to produce: To convince him of his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate condition, we need go no further but to his life and actions, the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry tenour whereof ſpeaks him wicked: But to convince the Formaliſt, it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to dive into his heart, to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his principles, ends, and intentions; and this is no eaſie matter; the heart is ſo full of windings, that neither we, nor himſelf can diſcover it: It is a grand cheat, 'twil pretend fair for God, Chriſt, and Holineſs: <hi>David</hi> ſuſpects his own heart, and therefore puts it under God's ſearch, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.21—<hi>end.</hi> Thus we have diſcovered ſome of thoſe inward impediments which render the Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of a Formaliſt more difficult, then of a Profane perſon: We come now to thoſe <hi>Ab extra;</hi> ſuch hinderances as are
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:98196:23"/>
without him, from others; and theſe I ſhall reduce to two heads, (omitting o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) <hi>viz.</hi> either 1. From Miniſters; or, 2. From People, eſpecially the Godly.</p>
               <p>Sect. 2. <hi>Outward Impediments of the Words effect upon the Formaliſt,</hi> viz. <hi>ſuch as proceed from others.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reaſon,</hi> 1 Something may be found in Miniſters, which renders the Converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Formaliſt very difficult, <hi>viz.</hi> Their want of skill and induſtry this way; God having appointed them as In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments in this work, and the effect be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more hardly or eaſily producible, not onely according to the skill of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Agent, but the aptitude or mep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of the Inſtrument he uſeth: Hence it follows, that the work miſcarries, through their ill-management of it. 'Tis true, in reference to God's abſolute Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, it matters not what the Inſtrument be; Clay and Spittle ſhall open blind eyes; The blowing of Ram's-horns ſhall be more prevalent then Iron-rams, to diſmantle a City; A Playſter of Figs ſhall cure a Boyl, or Plague-ſore, if God pleaſe: Nor is it leſs true, that the word is in its kind, a powerful weapon
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:98196:23"/>
to batter Fortifications, to level towring Imaginations, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4, 5. That it is ſharper then a Two-edged ſword, pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing to the dividing aſunder of Soul and Spirit—<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a critical Judg of the hearts, thoughts, intentions, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12. But yet it cuts according as it is managed and weilded; A <hi>Scanderbeg's</hi> arm can do wonders with an ordinary Sword; (though I would be loth to aſcribe ſo much to the Miniſters skill and induſtry as that inſtance may intimate, nor is it always according to a Miniſters ability or conſcientiouſneſs:) yet where there is a manifeſt defect of parts or piety, skill or induſtry, the work is leſs ſuccesfull. Now in nothing are the generality of God's Meſſengers more deficient, then in this Divine skill, to unfold the myſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Labyrinths of the heart of man; to uncaſe an Hypocrite, anatomize a For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maliſt, to get within men, and diſcover thoſe Depths of Satan that are in their hearts: This, though the higheſt Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and moſt neceſſary for a Miniſter, is leaſt ſtudied: The Eagle-ey'd School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men were but Bats and Owles in this kind of Learning: We alas! are more apt to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:98196:24"/>
ſpend our time and pains in high Specu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, curious Diſquiſitions, queſtions more tending to ſtrife, then the edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the hearer; then in this neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, very neceſſary ſtudy of unmasking the Formaliſt, and cutting the Thred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Hypocrite and the ſincere Chriſtian. It was Mr. <hi>Dod's</hi> expreſſion, that moſt Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> ſhot over the heads of their Auditors; ſure I am, too many ſhoot ſhort of their hearts. This proceeds partly from our unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with our own hearts; partly, from our not ſtudying the ſpirituality of Religion: Alas do we not draw men out of Profaneneſs into Formality, and there leave them? If we bring them up to a Form of Prayer, Hearing, Family-performances, do we not think the work done? We are too like ſome curious Carvers and Painters, that carve the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, draw the Lineaments, and lay the Colours of Chriſtianity upon them, but do not labour to beget in them the life of Chriſtians: We do not tell them as <hi>Mark</hi> 10.21. <hi>One thing is yet lacking:</hi> that power muſt be added to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, as the Soul to the Body. Oh that it might not be juſtly charged upon us,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:98196:24"/>
that we are content to ſee the image of Chriſtianity drawn upon our people! Beſides, it may partly proceed from hence, that the greateſt part of our Congregations conſiſting of prophane ones, we bend our Studies and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes mainly againſt them, and by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering things too generally, and indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly, we ſtrengthen the hands of the Formaliſt and Hypocrite. Add to all this, (which is, and ought to be for a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation) we lead our people no higher then a form by our example: 'Tis our too much formality in our lives, that teaches it our people; if they ſaw more of the power of godlineſs in us, our preaching would have more power to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get real godlineſs in them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reaſon</hi> 2. Something lies upon the generallity of Chriſtians, eſpecially the godly, which renders the converſion of a Formaliſt very difficult.</p>
               <p>As 1. The godly, not being able to diſcern them, (or if they diſcern them, having no warrant to ſeparate from them) do give them the right hand of fellowſhip, admit them into their moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate Society, lay them in their Boſoms, and they are reputed amongſt the beſt
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:98196:25"/>
of Chriſtians. This mightily confirms them in their good opinion of themſelves, and becomes an occaſion of hardning them againſt conviction. They abuſe this indulgence of the godly into their own obduration, and to the heightning of their ſecurity. I ſpeak not this, as blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the godly for admitting them (for Tares, though not Briars and Thorns, muſt grow amongſt the Wheat till Harveſt) but to ſhew, what bad uſe the hypocrite makes of the good eſteem he hath with the godly: Though perhaps, ſincere Chriſtians may juſtly deſerve to be blamed, for want of plain dealing with ſuch, whom they have juſt cauſe to ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of formality, or hypocriſie. Well, this, (as I ſaid) hardens the Formaliſt in his ſelf-conceit, and ſets him at a further diſtance to converſion. Under this ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Judas</hi> lay ſecure, and preſumed that his condition was as good as the reſt of the Apoſtles. A Formaliſt carries ſo ſmoothly, that the truly godly, (who are alwaies ſelf-ſuſpicious) are more apt to ſuſpect themſelves, then thoſe with whom they converſe. Now the godly (on the other hand) are ſhie of the company of prophane perſons, knowing they have
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:98196:25"/>
expreſs commands, to avoid unneceſſary converſe with ſuch, as, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. and this ſometimes, (through God's ſetting it upon their hearts) becomes an occaſion of putting them upon a more ſerious conſideration of their condition; even, a <hi>Cain</hi> fears and abhors the thought of being an Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſt; thoſe Cenſures of Suſpenſion and Excommunication, appointed by God himſelf, work by way of ſhame and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace. But,</p>
               <p n="3">3. There is ſo little livelineſs in the beſt of Chriſtians, that the Formaliſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes himſelf as good as the beſt, and ſo reſts in his preſent condition. Where there is ſomething of the power of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, yet there is too much of meer form; and this encourages others to reſt alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in a form. VVhere there is ſome life, there is too little livelineſs; the beſt do not to the life hold forth the word of life, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.16. There is ſomething in the lives of Chriſtians, to convince and condemn the Prophane; they ſee their ſwearing, drunkenneſs, Sabbath-break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> condemned in the practiſe of Chriſtians, ſhunning and abhorring thoſe ſins; but they do not ſo live, as to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:98196:26"/>
the Formality of thoſe amongſt them: There is not that warmth in their diſcourſes and duties, that vigour in their affections and actions, that may quicken and heat others. Men are apt to make a ſtand at others deadneſs, as the people did at the dead body of <hi>Amaſa,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.12.</p>
               <p>'Tis ſtoried of <hi>Janias,</hi> before his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, that meeting once with a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey-man, as he was in a journey, and fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into diſcourſe with him about divers points in Religion, he obſerved the plain Fellow, to talk ſo experimentally, with ſo much heartineſs and affection, as made him firſt begin to think, that there was ſomething more in thoſe Truths, then his Notional-humane Learning had yet diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered; which occaſioned his more ſerious inquiry into them, and afterward his Converſion. Livelineſs, and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onateneſs in Chriſtians, is a ſingular Spur to incite others; but alas! how rare is it? This wanting in the beſt, doth ſtrengthen the hands of the Formaliſt, and beget in him a conceit, that he is as good as the beſt. Thus we have laid down ſome of thoſe impediments, (both in himſelf, and from others) which lye
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:98196:26"/>
in the way of a Formaliſt's Converſion, and render it more difficult, then of the Prophane.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Miſaplication prevented.</head>
               <p>BEfore I come to Application, it will be requiſite to ſay ſomething for the preventing of m ſapplication. Some may poſſibly hence draw this Concluſion, That the next way to onverſion, is to turn Prophane; that to lay aſide Prayer, Hearing <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and to become a Swearer, Adulterer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is the beſt way to become a Saint; an inference much like that, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.8. <hi>Let us do evil that good may come;</hi> and <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.1.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 1 Tim. 5.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Let us continue in ſin, that grace may abound.</hi> But let ſuch * perverſe Diſputers know,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Though the word hath, many times, an eaſier influence upon the Prophane, then the Formal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>; yet this makes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for the comfort of Prophane per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, ſo continuing, though many ſuch are converted and ſaved; What is this to him that lives and dies unconverted? 'Tis as if one ſick of a Feaver, refuſing
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:98196:27"/>
the Phyſician's help, feeding and nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Diſeaſe, ſhould comfort himſelf in this, That his condition is better then one that is ſick of the Plague, becauſe many are by Phyſick cured of the one, few or none of the other; when the one as well as the other, is Mortal without the Phyſician's help. Though many Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Wretches are ſaved upon their Faith and Repentance, what comfort is it to thee that continueſt Prophane, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Faith or Repentance? If <hi>Zacheus</hi> the Publican, <hi>Magdalen</hi> the Harlot, <hi>Paul</hi> the Perſecutor, are converted and ſaved, canſt thou, who art an impenitent Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſor, Harlot, Perſecutor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> promiſe Salvation to thy ſelf? They are ſaved, not becauſe they were ſuch, but becauſe they Repent.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Though prophane perſons are more frequently converted, then Formaliſts, yet prophaneneſs is no cauſe of their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion. If you ſuppoſe ſo, you admit a Falacy, <hi>Non cauſae, pro cauſâ;</hi> aſſigning that the cauſe, which indeed is not: Many, being Prophane, are converted, but not becauſe they are Ptophane; they are converted from, not for their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſs. At moſt, it hath but an accidental
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:98196:27"/>
cauſality; as an enemy intending to kill you, may accidentally let out the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, and ſo intending to be your Murderer, may unwittingly, and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to his intention, prove your Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician; But that Prophaneneſs can have no proper cauſative influence into your converſion, will thus appear: If ſo, it muſt be ſuppoſed, either, 1. To move God to call you; or, 2. To diſpoſe, and incline you to converſion: but to imagine either of theſe, is very fooliſh and irrational.</p>
               <p>For the firſt, you muſt know, That no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing out of God himſelf can be an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducement to him, to call, or convert any; God's Eternal Decree, which is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Efflux of his own Will, and of his Free-Grace, is his onely Motive in this; See <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.29, 30. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.3, 4, 5, 6, 11. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9. 'Tis not the good works of any fore-ſeen, that move God to call them, (they being effects, not cauſes of converſion) much leſs then their evil works: what can be more abſur'd, then to ſuppoſe that that which God loaths, ſhould induce him to love us?</p>
               <p>And for the ſecond, 'tis equally ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd;
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:98196:28"/>
for how can that which is in the nature of it, an averſion from God, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce, as an effect, converſion to God? As rationally may we imagine darkneſs to be the cauſe of light, ſickneſs of health, death of life, as that ſin can any way be a cauſe of, or diſpoſe unto con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion. Could Prophaneneſs diſpoſe a man to Converſion, then it would follow, the more Prophane, the nearer to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion; which is all one, as to ſay, the nearer Hell, the nearer Heaven.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Neither is it the good that Forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts do, but their hypocriſie in doing, and the bad uſe they make of their good actions, that renders their Converſion difficult. Here a ſo you admit the ſame falacy, if you ſuppoſe their praying, hearing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to obſtruct their Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. Theſe duties rightly performed, are both means and evidences of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, and incumbent upon the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted. Hearing is the way to have Faith (and other Graces) begotten in us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.17 Prayer is preſcrib'd to <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> yet <hi>being in the g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                        <desc>••…</desc>
                     </gap> of bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs and bond of iniquity,</hi> in order to his Converſion, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.22. So we ma ſay of other-like duties: As Prophaneneſs is
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:98196:28"/>
not diſpoſitive to Converſion, ſo neither are Pious duties any hinderance, but fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance to it. Nay more, if ever you be Converted, you muſt do what they do, though not as they do. You muſt pray, hear, meditate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> though not in a form, as they do, but with power; not relying upon them when done, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying them, putting no confidence in them. 'Tis not the form of godlineſs that hinders Converſion, but becauſe it is but a form, and yet reſted in.</p>
               <p n="4">4. I may add, (though it's not ſo much to the buſineſs in hand) though Formaliſts hurt themſelves, yet they may be, and often are uſeful and beneficial to others; whereas the Prophane perſon is offenſive, or unprofitable to all: they may teach others, though not themſelves. Prophaneneſs, gives occaſion of ſtumb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and offence to them without; the Formaliſt's life carries ſome conformity to the Rule, (and is ſo far imitable) though his heart be naught and hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical; his practiſes are good, though his principles and ends be naught: Others may ſee what they ought to do in him; but the Prophane perſon, as his heart is naught, ſo his life is irregular, not to be
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:98196:29"/>
imitated. The formal perſons praying, hearing, &amp;c. may poſſibly excite others to do that in ſincerity, which they do in hypocriſie, their parts and performan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces may be uſeful to others, though ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidentally hurtful to themſelves. So that there's no Reaſon to draw ſuch an inference from the Doctrine in hand, or to ſuppoſe prophaneneſs the neareſt cut to converſion. If any will yet abuſe this Truth to their own obduration in wicked and debauched courſes, yet I hope what I have ſaid by way of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, will ſufficiently acquit me from the guilt of the blood of ſuch Souls: now for Application.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> The firſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of the Point, in ſeveral In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences, for Information, or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</head>
               <p>THe firſt Uſe may inform, or teach us ſeveral good Leſſons.</p>
               <p n="1">1. An outward conformity to the Rule of the word, is not converſion; 'tis more then cleanſing the life from groſs and palpable miſcarriages, or waſhing
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:98196:29"/>
the outſide of the Cup or Platter; if this were all, the Formaliſt would not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly go into the Kingdom of heaven be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the prophane perſon; but would be there already. If prayer, hearing, faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, talking religiouſly, were all, who would be ſaved ſooner then the Forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt? Then might we ſay of ſuch, as the Jews of the Scribes and Phariſees, if but two go to heaven, the one of them ſhould be a Formalliſt. Preſs him to reading, hearing, prayer, &amp;c. He will be ready to reply (and in ſome ſenſe truly) <hi>All theſe things have I done from my youth: what lack I yet?</hi> He can ſay with the Phariſee, Luke 18.11, 12. <hi>I thank God that I am not as other men are;</hi> and with <hi>Paul,</hi> Phil. 3.6. <hi>As touching the Righteouſneſs which is in the Law, blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs:</hi> his life is not ſpotted with any no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious, ſcandalous ſin; his Conſcience accuſeth him of nothing, but that which is incident to the beſt; in a word, take him, as to his outſide, his life, his fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quency in duty, &amp;c. you may rank him with thoſe of the higheſt form; yet this man may be poſſibly at a further diſtance to Chriſt, his converſion more hopeleſs, his heart more obdurate then the vileſt
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:98196:30"/>
drunkard, ſwearer, &amp;c. One thing, yea many things are lacking, eſpecially theſe three, which are eſſential to a Chriſtian.</p>
               <p n="1">1. He wants a throughly humbling ſight of ſin, eſpecially of the ſin of his nature and of his heart; he ſees not that Atheiſm, pride, unbelief, hypocriſie, &amp;c. which lodg in his boſom: this is a main thing in order to converſion. <hi>Paul</hi> had all above-mentioned while a Phariſee, but till the law revived and he died, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.9. till he ſaw himſelf carnal ſold under ſin, he remained uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted. The formaliſt is ready to ſay with that proud Monk, <hi>Iſidorè, non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beo dominè quod mihi ignoſcas,</hi> I have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that needs a pardon; but if ever the true work be begun he muſt change his note, and cry out with <hi>David, Pſ.</hi> 25.11. <hi>Pardon my ſin, for it is great;</hi> and with the <hi>Publican,</hi> Luke 18.13. <hi>God be merciful to me a ſinner.</hi> There is no converſion without ſome conviction, none were ever ſaved (in Gods ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry way of working) but they have ſeen themſelves loſt. There will be ſome ſenſe of ſin, and ſolicitouſneſs about the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of it, in all thoſe that are truly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:98196:30"/>2. He wants ſelf-denyal, to wit, a total and abſolute diſclaim of his own righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs; abnegation of ſelf is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, praerequiſite to acceptation of Chriſt; this is more then whole burnt offerings and ſacrifices. He can do duties, but cannot deny them; he cannot with <hi>Paul,</hi> count all loſs and dung for Chriſt, &amp;c. <hi>Phil.</hi> 37.10. He doth, and expects for doing; looks for heaven not as a gift of grace, or the purchaſe of Chriſts blood, but as wages for working. He is much of the temper of thoſe two Monks, or Popiſh Prieſts, the o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e whereof proud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly challenges God, <hi>Redd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> mihi vitam aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam quam debes.</hi> Pay me eternal life, which thou oweſt me; the other as ſcornfully refuſeth heaven as a gift, <hi>Coelum gratis non accepiam,</hi> I will not take heaven on free-coſt; now hence, all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes odious to God that ſuch a one doth: his duties no more acceptable then killing a man, cutting off a dogs neck, offering Sw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nes blood, or bleſſing an Idol, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.3. He is but (<hi>Ephraim</hi>-like, <hi>Hoſ</hi> 10.1) <hi>An empty Vine br nging forth fruit unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</hi> Self is that great Idol, which (like <hi>Bell</hi> in the <hi>Apocryphal</hi> ſtory) devours all; ſelf is prayed to, ſelf is praiſed, ſelf is
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:98196:31"/>
the principle and end, the <hi>Alpha</hi> &amp; <hi>Omega</hi> of all this ſpeaks him ſhort of true con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion.</p>
               <p n="3">3. He wants ſincerity (which is Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical perfection) in all he doth: that which he doth, is good, but he doth it not well. The Scripture diſtinguiſheth betwixt doing that which is right in the ſight of the Lord, and doing it with a perfect heart, <hi>Aſa</hi>'s heart was perfect all his days, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.17. <hi>And he did that which was good and right in the eyes of the Lord his God.</hi> Chap. 14.2. not ſo <hi>Amaziah,</hi> Chapt. 25.2. <hi>He did that which was right—but not with a perfect heart:</hi> God looks at the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, manner, and end of our actings, as well as the matter; here the Formaliſt is deficient: <hi>non factum ſed modus in culpâ:</hi> the matter is good, but the manner is culpable. God may ſay to ſuch as the Jews of old, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.8. <hi>I will not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove thee for thy ſacrifices or thy burnt offerings to have been continually before me;</hi> I will not blame thee for neglect of, but want of ſincerity in duty: God will draw up a charge againſt them, like that <hi>Zech.</hi> 7.5, 6. <hi>When ye faſted and mourned, did ye at all faſt unto me,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:98196:31"/>
even to me? And when ye did eat, and when ye did drink, did not ye eat for your ſelves, and drink for your ſelves?</hi> They failed, you ſee, in the end of their duties: Self, and not God, was their End; and this is a great piece of inſincerity. Converſion, if right, not onely rectifies a mans acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but chiefly his Principles and Ends; ſo that the Formaliſt, in this, appears to be ſhort of true Converſion.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A ſecond Leſſon we may hence learn, is this, <hi>viz.</hi> The Reaſon, or at leaſt a reaſon why Converſion is ſo rare in theſe laſt days: Men are got up to a Form, and there they ſtick: It was long ſince foretold, that Formality ſhould be a ſin of the Laſt days, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5. There are few but they have got ſome know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, and do ſomething in a Form, and they think this enough, and all. Some Diſeaſes are called <hi>Opprobria Medico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> the ſhame or reproach of Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, becauſe they cannot find out the cauſe and rule of them. This, if any, is the <hi>Opprobrium Miniſtrorum,</hi> very hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcovered, and more hardly cured. Though it cannot be denied, that there is too much Prophaneneſs in the World; yet even Prophaneneſs it ſelf is got under
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:98196:32"/>
this ſhelter: A Form of Godlineſs is many times found amongſt thoſe that are under the Power of open Wickedneſs. Relig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> g ins in breadth, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t hath more Profeſſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s and Practiſers of it in a Form; but loſeth in depth and height, never ſo little ſincerity and ſeriouſneſs in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion and practice of it. Knowledg and Means abound; Light gets into the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. Men cannot keep their Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences from being Clamourous, without doing ſomething; loth they are to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go their ſweet, their profitable ſins: Hence ariſe a civil Commotion, (as the Philoſopher ſpeaks of the morally wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, their Souls are at odds with themſe ves) light and luſt are together by the ears; now to take up the quarrel and comprim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ze the differerence, Satan and their own hearts find out this expedient, to ſet up a form of Godlineſs, that under this cloak they may more ſecurely practiſe the power of ungodlineſs: they will do ſomething that is good, ſuppoſing they may have the better leave to do evil; when men are got to this, they ſtick at it, and make it their <hi>non ultra:</hi> thus they think to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie both Intereſts, <hi>viz.</hi> of their ſins,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:98196:32"/>
and of their ſouls. 'Tis true, there are Formaliſts of different forms and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees; ſome more groſs and palpable, others that ſpin a finer thread, and waſte more in the dark; but this ſin, more or leſs, is to be found in the generality of profeſſed Chriſtians, and this renders Converſion a very rare and difficult work.</p>
               <p n="3">3. This ſhews us, that (although no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is common, yet) nothing is more dangerous, to ſtep out of Prophaneneſs, into Formality: how ordinary is it for notorious ſinners, when beaten out of open wickedneſs, to take Sanctuary in a form of Godlineſs? What's this, but to run further from God, while we ſeem to come nearer him? at beſt but to come out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and ſtay in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? ſuch men turn ſin (like ſome thief or lewd Companion) out of the ſtreet-door, and then receive it in at a back-door, lodging it in the ſecret Chamber of their hearts; they retire out of the field of a more open hoſtility againſt God and Holineſs; but betake them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into an impregnable Caſtle, where they ſet God and Chriſt at Defiance: un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a pretence of Kiſſing, they do more
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:98196:33"/>
certainly kill Chriſt: ſhunning <hi>Scylla,</hi> they fall into <hi>Charybdis:</hi> thinking to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive God by a ſhew, they deceive them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves really. For,</p>
               <p n="1">1. You, (that I may turn my ſpeech to ſuch) do but more obſtruct the way to your own Converſion; get fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of the reach and power of the Word: the Plague, when it comes out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in a boyl or ſore, is leſs dangerous, then when it ſtrikes inward, and ſeizeth upon the Brain or Vitals. Formality is but a ſtriking in of that diſeaſe, which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly appeared on the Face and Body, and therefore makes it more incurable. 'Tis ſad to think, how many have left the fouler way of Prophaneneſs, in which they were walking towards Hell, and are now more certainly, and ſwiftly poſting thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in the cleaner way of Formality! Well, let me tell you, the Divel thinks none ſo ſurely his, as thoſe, who ſerve him under Chriſt's Livery. They that think themſelves Free, and yet are not, are moſt likely to continue in Bondage, He is twofold more the Child of Hell, who hath got a Cloak of Religion to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his Rags and filthineſs withal; and hath got the Art to keep up a practiſe of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:98196:33"/>
duty, and a courſe of ſin together. That diſeaſe is moſt Mortal oftentimes, that is leaſt fealt: Formality onely ſerves to Brawn the heart, and Sear the conſcience, and then there's but little hope of ſuch a ſoul's Converſion. He that is become inſenſible, (and ſuch is the Formaliſt) is next door to incurable.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As you do more effectually ſhut Heaven's door upon you, ſo you open a wider door into Hell; (that I may allude to that Scripture, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.11.) A more abundant entrance you have into Satan's Kingdom: your evidences are hereby made clearer, your title ſurer. Hell is the hypocrite's Fee-ſimple, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.51. The nearer Heaven, if you fall ſhort of it, the greater will your fall be, and the heavier your condemnation, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.20, 21. &amp;c. <hi>If you have eſcaped the pollutions of the world—and are again entangled,</hi> (as certainly you will be, if you reſt in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality) <hi>your later end will be worſe then your beginning; better you had never known the way of righteouſneſs, then afterward to turn from the holy commandment.</hi> A great part of Hell will doubtleſs be a ſad recapitulation of the poſſibilities, proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities, advantages, convictions, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:98196:34"/>
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which we had, and ſlighted; the more of theſe here, the more of Hell hereafter. And who then may expect a hotter Hell then your ſelves? Oh, will it not be a heart-cutting conſideration, to think how many ſteps you had taken, and all in vain, for want of one ſtep further? Yea, to think, that there are many now in glory, who took leſs pains (as to the matter, and frequency of duty) then thou didſt, who ſhalt yet lye down in the Lake of Fire and Brimſtone for ever.</p>
               <p n="4">4. This ſhews us, that the Formaliſt hath no reaſon to boaſt, or lift himſelf in his own conceit, above the prophaneſt wretch that he ſees or knows of: 'Tis ordinary with ſuch to bleſs themſelves with the Phariſee, <hi>Luke</hi> 18.11. <hi>God, I thank thee, that I am not as other men are, nor as this Publican.</hi> To ſtand upon their compariſons, or rather diſpariſons <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 65.5. <hi>Stand by thy ſelf; Come not near me, I am holier then thou:</hi> but there is a checking word follows, <hi>Theſe are a ſmoke in my noſe, and a fire that burneth all the day;</hi> highly and continually offenſive to God. 'Tis a ſpeech much like that o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our Saviour to <hi>Peter, Get thee behind me
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:98196:34"/>
Satan, thou art an offence unto me.</hi> Poor deluded, ſelf-deluding ſouls! You think your ſtate incomparably better then your prophane Friend or Neighbour; when, alas, it's worſe, in this at leaſt, that you think it better: What difference do you think, will God make betwixt an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen Enemy, and a counterfeit Friend; ſurely, if any, the later is worſe. God ſeems to be puſled, and at a <hi>non-plus,</hi> what to do with ſuch as thou art, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.15. <hi>I would thou wert either hot or cold;</hi> but <hi>verſ.</hi> 16. comes to a peremptory and terrible reſolution; <hi>So then, becauſe thou art neither hot nor cold, I will ſpue thee out of my mouth:</hi> Is this a condition to be proud of? What more loathſom then vomit? Can the vileſt wretch on-earth, undergo a heavier doom? Indeed, could not God find thee out, thy caſe might be more hopeful, but he can, and will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mask and uncaſe thee: Then thy condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will be ſo much the worſe, by how much better it ſeemed to thee, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 125. 5. <hi>Such as turn aſide unto their crooked wayes, the Lord ſhall lead them forth with the workers of iniquity.</hi> Such are the wayes of the hypocritical Formaliſt, tortuous and crooked; full of windings,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:98196:35"/>
and turnings, like the Hare's doublings before the Dogs; but God will find them out, <hi>and lead them forth with the wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>rs of iniquity,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In tortuoſi talibus.</note> 
                  <hi>i. e.</hi> They ſhall be numbred with the prophane and open Sinners, and fall with them into the ſame condemnation. Let me then ſay to thee, as the Penitent Thief to his Fellow, <hi>Luke</hi> 23.40. <hi>Doſt not thou fear God, ſeeing thou art in the ſame condemnation?</hi> Why boaſteſt thou a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the prophane, when both muſt lye down together in the ſame Hell? Yea thou, in the hotter place: The Tares, as well as Briars and Thorns, muſt be burnt with fire unquenchable, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.30, 40. Your boaſting therefore is not good.</p>
               <p n="5">5. This may intimate a twofold duty incumbent on Miniſters, in reference to this ſin of Formality.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Let us take heed of driving our Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple out of Prophaneneſs into Formality, and there leaving them. What skill and prudence is neceſſary, ſo to manage our Work, that we, not onely draw upon them the Lineaments, but beget in them the life of Chriſtianity: Leſt we be like the unskilful Chyrurgion, to skin the ſore, and let it feſter inwardly; this is inſtead
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:98196:35"/>
of curing, to render them more incura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Two things will much conduce to a thorow work.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Let us be ſure to preſs an inward, as well as outward change; labour we to get into their hearts, and convince them, that the Root of all their Malignity is there, according to that of our Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.19. Let us tell them, and tell them again, <hi>That they muſt be renewed in the ſpirit of their minds, Epheſ.</hi> 4.23. That it is not enough <hi>to cleanſe their hands,</hi> except they alſo <hi>purifie their hearts, Jam.</hi> 4.8. That 'tis not onely the courſe of their lives, but chiefly and primarily the frame of their hearts that muſt be chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: while we onely preſs outward Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, and performance of duties, we do but teach them to do as Chriſtians, not to be Chriſtians; 'tis good to begin at the heart, and bring the diſeaſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Let us be much in preſſing Faith and Obedience to Chriſt, as well as Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and Reformation. Repentance towards God, and Faith towards our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, were the ſum of <hi>Pauls</hi> Doctrine, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.20. Both muſt be preached; the former in ſubordination
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:98196:36"/>
to the latter: <hi>Luther</hi> uſed to ſay, he that can well diſtinguiſh betwixt Law and Goſpel, is a good Divine; I ſay, he that can join them well together, is the skilful Preacher: we ſhould be very care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful that we ſeparate not Faith and Duty, Law and Goſpel, or make thoſe oppoſite, which are ſubordinate; while we preſs Repentance, Prayer, Hearing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with little or no mention of Chriſt, we teach men to be Loyaliſts; while we preach Chriſt, Free-Grace, the Saints Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> without the Law, we teach men to be Libertines, and Licentious An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinomiſts: The mean is beſt; a pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent mixture of Loyal ſeverity, with Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel ſweetneſs, is the way to make men thorough Chriſtians.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The other branch of our duty is this, That we bend our ſtudy much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this ſin, it being the ſin of the age we live in. What charge the King of <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria</hi> gave concerning the King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 22.31. <hi>Fight neither with ſmall nor great,</hi> &amp;c. The ſame ſhould our care be as to this ſin: 'Tis the Devil's laſt and ſtrongeſt hold: beat him out here, and we are Conquerors. Two things (omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting other) I commend to this purpoſe.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:98196:36"/>1. (To make us more able for this work) Let us diligently obſerve the wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and formality of our own hearts: For as it is, <hi>Proverbs</hi> 27.19. <hi>As in water, face anſwereth to face; ſo the heart of man to man.</hi> (Though I will not be confident that's the ſenſe of that Text) we are all of the ſame mould: Books may make us able, but this will make us profitable Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters: The beſt way to fit our Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons for others hearts, is to try them upon, or rather to dig them out of our own: What our people do moſt indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriouſly ſtrive to hide from us, <hi>viz.</hi> the naughtineſs of their hearts, we may in deſpight of them ſee in our own: (and poſſibly this may be one reaſon why the Wiſdom of God hath choſen men of like infirmities with others, to be the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of the Word.) Well, my Brethren, let's but ſhoot home at our own hearts, and it's a thouſand to one if we hit not ſome, yea, many in our Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p n="2">2. (To make us more ſucceſsful in this work) Pray over our ſtudies: Some ſteep ſeeds before they put them into the Earth, and water them after: How well might we hope that ſpiritual ſeed would
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:98196:37"/>
thrive, that hath Prayer to go before, and follow it: and truly, if ever we have need to pray, it is when we are to grap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with this ſin. This formal Devil will ſcarce out without prayer and faſting; What need have we to beg that the ſearcher of hearts will direct the arrow of his Word to the heart? The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle in <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12, 13. ſpeaking of the words diſcovering power, ties with a ſtrange connexion, the Omniſcience of God to it. Surely, if the All-knowing God do not more immediately concur, the Word will not ſo pierce to the divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding aſunder of the Soul and Spirit, joints and marrow, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 'Tis fabled of <hi>Pigma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion,</hi> that having made the Pourtraicture of a curious Woman, falling in love with it, he prayed to <hi>Venus,</hi> and ſhe put life into it: Have we drawn the amiable Picture, or carved the lovely image of a Chriſtian upon any of our people? O let's beg down life into them from God.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Once more: We may hence learn, that God looks not at worthineſs or unworthineſs, at preparitory diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, previous qualifications, or that Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh fiction of merit of congruity in thoſe whom he calls: (I deſire here to
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:98196:37"/>
be underſtood of what we may imagine to diſpoſe a man, or put him in a nearer capacity to converſion; otherwiſe there is no ſuch thing as fitneſs or unfitneſs really, as to Gods Omnipotency) ſhould God judg as man judgeth, or look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the outward appearance, as man look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, Whom ſhould he ſooner call then the Formaliſt? were we to gueſs accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to carnal Reaſon, whom the Lord would chuſe, would we not ſay of the Formaliſt, as <hi>Samuel</hi> of <hi>Jeſſes</hi> eldeſt ſon;<note place="margin">1 Sam. 16.</note> ſurely the Lords annointed is before him? theſe ſeem to meet God half way, and not to be far from the Kingdom of God. Who would take (as was before hinted) the knottieſt, crookedſt timber to lay in his building? the rougheſt ſtones to make his wall? yet ſo it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes God to do: God looks with other eyes then we do. <hi>Mat</hi> 9.12, 13. Chriſt came not to call the righteous, but ſinners to repentance. God delights to make all his works Creations, and to build where there is no appearance of founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and this to exclude mans boaſting. He will have his grace to be, and to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear free. But to proceed to a ſecond Uſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:98196:38"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> The ſecond and third <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of the Point, <hi>Viz.</hi> Terror to the Formaliſt, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries of ſuch.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>2</label> THe ſecond Uſe may ſerve to pull down the pride and haughtineſs of the ſelf-conceited Formaliſt, and to ſtrike terror into his heart: This Text and Doctrine may be like the fingers and hand-writing to <hi>Belſhazzar, Dan.</hi> 5.5. And paſſeth the ſame ſentence upon him as that did, Thou art weighed in the ballance, and found wanting. How doth the Formaliſt bleſs himſelf in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the prophane? He would not for a world be as they are; when alas, he is worſe. If I may ſay of the uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, That one is further from conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion then another, (as that Text ſeems to intimate, <hi>Mark</hi> 13.34. Thou art not far, &amp;c.) then theſe ſurely are at the far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt diſtance. That fore-cited Text, <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.12.13. Chriſt came not to call the righteous, but ſinners to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; ſeems to hint, that ſuch ſelf-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitedly righteous perſons, are out of
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:98196:38"/>
the care and call of Chriſt, and that's ſad. But I cannot expect that any ſhould take home this Terror, till it be charged home upon them; till Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſay, Thou art the man: we are apt to catch at comforts, and decline terrors; it will be neceſſary therefore, to give ſome Signes and Characters of the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maliſt (though ſomething hath been already hinted) that ſo being convinced, he may apply it.</p>
               <p>This may (if you pleaſe) be a diſtinct <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>3</label> Uſe of Examination. To give you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſome Notes of ſuch:</p>
               <p n="1">1. He whoſe duties and perſonal righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs ſtand in oppoſition, not in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordination to Chriſt and his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, is the perſon we ſpeak of: poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly his Baptiſm and Education make him affect the name of Chriſtian; but he ſees not the abſolute neceſſity of Chriſts righteouſneſs to juſtifie and ſave him; ſuppoſing he hath enough in his own ſtore. Had this man heard Chriſt ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his ſufferings in order to mans ſalvation, he would have been ready with <hi>Peter,</hi> to ſay, as <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.22. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ſpare thy ſelf; or as <hi>Judas</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the precious ointment, To what
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:98196:39"/>
end is all this waſte? He may be a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed enemy to Popery, yet hath in him this Popiſh principle that he can keep the Commandments, and it may be ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pererogate alſo. ſuch a one deals with Chriſt, as thoſe women the Prophet ſpeaks of, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 4.1. We will (ſay they) eat our own bread, and wear our own apparrel, onely let us be called by thy name, to take away our reproach; So they will be cloathed with their own Righteouſneſs; onely they love the name Chriſtian, becauſe its a name of honor: How is it then? the more ſtrict and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thou ſeemeſt to thy ſelf, doth Chriſt ſeem of leſs neceſſity to thee? do thy duties ſet thee further off, or bring thee nearer Chriſt? doſt thou live more within, and upon thy ſelf? ſurely if ſo, to thee this terror belongs; 'Tis quite contrary with the ſincere Chriſtian, his duties and performances drive him near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Chriſt: ſee <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.3.-10. though he grow in inherent holineſs, yet he grows daily more apprehenſive of the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of imputed righteouſneſs, becauſe he ſees more of Gods holineſs, the laws purity and ſtrictneſs, and the impuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and filthineſs of his own heart: when
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:98196:39"/>
he hath done all, he cries out, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Servant!</hi> and woe to me, for my Duties, Prayers, Hearings, Graces, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> if I had not a Mediator. When he riſes higheſt in Duty or gracious actings, yet his ſuit to Chriſt (as <hi>Ruth's</hi> to <hi>Boaz, Ruth.</hi> 3.9.) is, <hi>Spread thy skirt over me.</hi> 'Tis remarkable, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3 3.<hi>For we are the Circumciſion which worſhip God in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and rejoyce in Chriſt Jeſus, and have no confidence in the fleſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. (Which is the root of the former) He whoſe Duties and Holineſs are the fuel of Pride, is the man we enquire af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; Thus it was with the Phariſees, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.5. <hi>Luke</hi> 18.11, 12. <hi>John</hi> 7.48. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality comes off ordinarily more proud from a Duty, and goes on the next time more ſelf-confident (except perhaps God hath notably cut him ſhort, as to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of his gifts:) True, pride may ruſh (as one ſaith) into the heart of a ſincere Chriſtian; but it reſts, grows, is cheriſhed in the heart of a Hypocrite: where Pride leads on in any Duty,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dike</hi> on the Hearts Deceitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</note> yet Humility brings him off: what the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere perſon wants in antecedent direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing humility, he makes up in ſubſequent and correcting humility, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 32.26.
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:98196:40"/>
                  <hi>Hezekiah</hi> was humbled for the pride of his heart: a true Chriſtian is humbled for his Pride, an Hypocrite is proud of his Humility: There's a Monitor within the ſincere Chriſtians heart, that's often jogging him, and brings him down when he begins to ſwell. Try then, is this worm of pride bred and nouriſhed by thy duties? Doeſt thou pray, and hear, and diſcourſe thy ſelf more proud, haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſelf-conceited? 'Tis a ſad ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome thou art yet but a Formaliſt: 'Tis ſtoried,<note place="margin">Heylin.</note> that the Iſle of <hi>Man</hi> (the Title being doubted whether it belonged to <hi>Britain</hi> or <hi>Ireland</hi>) was adjudged to <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> becauſe it foſter'd venemous Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents brought from thence into it: Sure I am, if thy duties foſter and cheriſh this venomous Serpent of Pride, they are the duties of a Formaliſt, not a ſincere Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.</p>
               <p n="3">3. He that is altogether a ſtranger to Godly ſorrow, Humiliation for ſin, (and this is the cauſe of both the former) he that never knew what compunction or contrition meant, whoſe heart was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver broken up, and furrowed with the Plow of conviction; who hath had but a ſuperficial work, hath but cleanſed the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:98196:40"/>
outſide of the Cup or Platter? 'Tis ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable, <hi>The ſtony ground received the word</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) Matth. 13.20. <hi>immediately with joy, but ſoon witherered:</hi> whereof the Evangeliſt <hi>Matthew,</hi> Chap. 13.5. gives the reaſon, <hi>becauſe it had not depth of Earth:</hi> Luke, Chap. 8.6. <hi>becauſe it had not moiſture:</hi> Both the Evangeliſts, as alſo <hi>Mark</hi> Chap. 4.16. tells us, They received the Word with joy and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: What can be underſtood by depth of earth, and moiſture, but heatings and meltings by Humiliation? This the ſtony ground wanted; and therefore they being yet a rock not broken, not hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, the ſeed though ſuddenly ſpringing up, withers, and comes to nothing: heat and moiſture are joint-cauſes of growth and fruitfulneſs; the latter with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the former drowns and ſuffocates the ſeed; the former without the latter doth ſcorch and wither it: and this is the caſe of this ground, they have ſome heat of joy and raptures, which (like the flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering rays of the <hi>Aprill</hi> Sun) draw forth ſome early bloſſoms; but when ſome cold chilling froſts, or ſcorching heats come in the following Month, they are either nipt by the one, or ſcorched and ſhrunk
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:98196:41"/>
up by the other: Praemature fruits ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver come to maturity: The Child that thruſts its ſelf forth into the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore its time, ſeldom proves long-liv'd. Such are Formaliſts, they haſtily catch at Chriſt, before they are humbled for ſin, or melted by godly ſorrow, and therefore do as quickly forſake him: The like may be gathered from that other Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable of the wiſe and fooliſh builders, <hi>Luke</hi> 6.47, 48. The wiſe Builder, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, digged deep, and laid his foundation on a rock; the fooliſh built without a foundation on the Earth; ſurely Humiliation and thorow convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is (at leaſt in part) the import of that digging deep; and for want of this digging, the building doth, <hi>molâ ſuà ruere,</hi> fall by its own weight: for want of theſe dews and moiſtures the root is dried up from beneath, and above the bud is cut off, <hi>Job</hi> 18.16. As the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, ſo the ſpiritural birth is attended with pangs. Now the Formaliſt is one that never felt theſe, or not to purpoſe; never ſo as to bring him off his own righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, or to ſubdue his will to an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance of Chriſt upon Goſpel terms. But here I deſire to be rightly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood;
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:98196:41"/>
I preſcribe not ſuch a meaſure of humiliation as neceſſary, nor to all the like meaſure: there is great difference as to the manner, meaſure, and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of it; all are not thrown upon the ground, and deprived of their ſight as <hi>Paul</hi> was; all walk not in the Region of the ſhadow of death, nor go bowed down 18 years with a ſpirit of Infirmity: To ſome God comes in a fire, thunder and whirlwind, to others in a ſtill voice; as God teacheth us to put a difference, <hi>Jude</hi> 22,23. ſo himſelf doth doth; on ſome he hath compaſſion, others he ſaves with fear, pulling them out of the fire; the convictions and humiliation of ſome are more ſenſible &amp; terrible, like the breaking of ſtones with a hammer; they are brought by the gates of Hell to Heaven; of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, more ſweet, kindly and inſenſible, like the melting of wax before the fire, and Ice or Snow before the Sun. The Souls of ſome are taken by ſtorm, others by a long and tedious ſiege and battery; ſome are ſurprized, as it were, by ſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagem, and ſome ſurrendred upon Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley; yea, ſome are ſo wrought upon, that the firſt (ſenſible) work they experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, is Grace, drawing them to a volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:98196:42"/>
reſignment of their ſouls to God. All theſe worketh our gracious God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his own Will and Pleaſure; nor can any certain ſtated Rules be laid down about the various workings of God with poor ſouls. Nevertheleſs, theſe two things I conceive may be ſafely aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted:</p>
               <p n="1">1. That before a ſoul is brought, or upon a ſouls coming over to Chriſt, he hath ſuch a convincing ſight of ſin, and of his own ſin original and actual, with ſuch a meaſure of compunction &amp; contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (be it leſs or more) as doth make him both ſee an abſolute neceſſity of Chriſt, and willingly cloſe with him upon Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel conditions. (I ſpeak here of God's working upon the <hi>adult.</hi>) 'Tis not meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the love of Chriſt, or his excellency appehended, that attracts the ſoul to him; but withal, he ſees he ſtands in need of him, and is undone without him. I would fain know of any of thoſe pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Patrons and Aſſertors of free-Grace, how a ſoul can have any apprehenſions of the love of Chriſt to purpoſe, without ſome praevious apprehenſions and convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of its own ſinfulneſs and miſery: Is it not the very Emphaſis of the love of
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:98196:42"/>
Chriſt, that while we were yet ſinners he died for us? <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.8. <hi>That when we were loſt, he came to ſeek and ſave us?</hi> take away this ſenſe of ſin and miſery, and you take away the very accent of Chriſt's love. Is not this the language of a Soul under the moſt kindly workings? O in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Love! that ſuch a vile, ſinful, loſt wretch as I am ſhould be ſought for, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired after! much like the language of <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> to <hi>David,</hi> 2 Sam. 9.8. <hi>What is thy ſervant, that thou ſhouldeſt look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch a dead dog as I am?</hi> And <hi>Ch.</hi> 19.28. <hi>All my fathers houſe were but dead men before my Lord the King, yet didſt thou ſet thy ſervant among them that did eat at thy table.</hi> Here's deep and deep; depth of Miſery, and depth of Mercy; theſe jointly apprehended, melt the heart of a poor ſinner, and make it as water, or rather as wax, fit for any Divine im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion: ſo that there is in the ſoul, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der moſt ingenuous and kindly workings, ſenſe of ſin, and ſorrow for it, though ſwallowed up in the joyful ſenſe of God's love in Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
               <p n="2">2. And after a ſoul is come to Chriſt, the frame of the heart is ſuch, that it's ready to grieve and melt upon the ſight
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:98196:43"/>
and conviction of a ſin now committed, or the remembrance of a ſin formerly acted: <hi>Hezekiah</hi> humbled himſelf for the pride of his heart, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 32.26. We find <hi>Peter</hi> in the ſame temper, and <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> often; the ſtone being taken out of the heart, there is an habitual tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ready to exert it ſelf in kindly meltings, upon ſight of any unkindneſſes, and diſingenuous actings towards God, Chriſt, or the Spirit: Now to both theſe, the Formaliſt is a ſtranger: his will was never ſubdued, his heart never molified ſo far, as to go out of himſelf: Bring this note home, and try your ſtate by it, I beſeech you.</p>
               <p n="4">4 He is a Formaliſt, who though he is conſtant in the matter, yet is little or not at all conſcientious in the manner of duty: That it be done, he is very care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; but how, he regards not. The For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Jews were ſo conſtant at their ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, that there God will not blame them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.8. The ſincere Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an is no leſs troubled for his careleſneſs, cuſtomarineſs, wandrings and diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in, then for his omiſſions of duty; he accounts that, as not done, which is not done with ſome ſuitableneſs of affection,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:98196:43"/>
and exerciſe of grace: he thinks he hath but mockt God, and taken his Name in vain: But this troubles not the Forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt; he is a good Church-man (as they call him) conſtant at his Family-du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and never matters how cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorily and ſlubbringly they are perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: his care is to get it done, the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Chriſtians, to get it well done; think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf never the better for that Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that makes him not better; never the nearer for that which brings him not fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of himſelf, and nearer God. Try then; Canſt thou never remember the time when thy heart ſmote thee for thy negligence in, as well as neglect of Duty? Doſt thou go on merrily and confidently in a cold, dull, heartleſs courſe of Religious Performances? 'Tis a ſad ſign thou art yet a Formaliſt, and to thee the Text ſpeaks terror.</p>
               <p n="5">5. He is a Formaliſt whoſe Duties do no execution upon his ſins; he Prays, and ſins; Hears, and ſins; goes in a round, as a Horſe in a Mill: Take him at his Prayers, you may hear him per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps confeſſing his Worldlineſs; but take him in the World, and you find him as covetous, as griping, as apt to defraud
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:98196:44"/>
as ever: he comes off his duties, as if he had but begg'd leave to ſin; yea, ſin gets ſtrength by his performances: As the Harlot, <hi>Prov.</hi> 7.14, 15. <hi>I have Peace-offerings by me, this day I have paid my vows. Come, let us take our fill of love</hi>— So he thinks his morning and evening-Duties procure him liberty to ſin all the day; when he hath heard, though the Word was never ſo pierceing, he never thinks more of it, to reform his heart or life by it; that he hath heard ſatifies him, never thinking what, or to what end he hath heard; hence it is that no execution is done upon his luſts. Now with the ſincere Chriſtian 'tis far otherwiſe; his Duties give ſin a ſhake, looſen it at the root: True indeed, a corruption may out-live many a Prayer, Sermon, Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation-day, without any ſenſible de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay; yea, may ſeem to get head, and grow more turbulent; yet every Duty rightly performed, doth ſomething to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the mortification of it: as in cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting down a tree, every ſtroak doth not bring it down, yet ſome chips are cut off; and in battering a Fort, every ſhot doth not beat it down, yet makes it weaker, and prepares it for the next. So every
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:98196:44"/>
Duty doth ſomething weaken ſin, at leaſt thus; for that it increaſes the Soul's ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of it, and puts upon him a freſh en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement to purſue it to the death: exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine then; doth ſin get ſtrength by thy Religious duties? doſt thou grow into more love and liking of thy boſome cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions? (for that's the ſureſt evidence of ſins growth:) Then haſt thou juſt cauſe to ſuſpect thy ſelf of formality, and to apply this terror to thy ſelf.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The Formaliſt is ordinarily full of confidence and ſelf-conceit, very ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilious towards poor bruiſed reeds, and doubting ſouls: he looks upon the weak Believer as no body in compariſon of himſelf. Thus you ſee it in the Phariſees, <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.48. <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.9— 12. <hi>Paul</hi> was once of this temper, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.9. He was alive without the Law once; <hi>i. e.</hi> highly conceited, and ſtrongly confident of his good condition: ſo the Formaliſt ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom ſuſpects himſelf, never is at a loſs for his Evidences. The Devil befriends him, and helps him up to this Pinacle; he is not more an enemy to true ſaving Faith, then a friend to Preſumption: The ſincere Chriſtian (on the other hand) is very ſuſpitious, often trying, dougbt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:98196:45"/>
ſearching; works out his ſalvation with fear and trembling. 'Tis true ſome healthy, well-complexion'd Chriſtians, (but oh how rare are they!) keep up faith in a lively and conſtant exerciſe; can look within the veil, and are not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to thoſe frequent toſſings and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings as others; but then they do not brow-beat, and carry ſcornfully and contemptuouſly towards thoſe that have not attained to their Meaſure: they are very tender towards the weakeſt Lambs in Chriſt's fold, and can ſympathize in their weakneſſes, and help to bear their Infirmities. That ſuppoſed aſſurance that is joined with the contempt of weak ones, and ſeparated from a holy, humble, watchful walking with God, is a ſure note of a Formaliſt. There is fear and jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie in the beſt; <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 139. 20—<hi>end.</hi> profeſſes his ſincerity, yet ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects there ma be ſome way of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in him: ſo that if thou haſt high pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptions, and low performances, ſtrong confidence upon weak grounds, and this lifts thee up in thy own conceit above thy weak brethren; conclude thy ſelf but yet a Formaliſt.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:98196:45"/>7. The Formaliſt hath ſome regard to the matter of the firſt Table, little to the ſecond: Piety, as to the face of it, he practiſeth, but equity and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity he little looks at, perhaps nor ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety neither, he thinks his duties towards God may excuſe his deficiencies towards men (And herein by the way, the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raliſt and Formaliſt differ; the former being onely or chiefly for ſecond table duties, though both do <hi>convenire in tertio,</hi> agree in this third thing, that they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect Chriſt, and put confidence in their own righteouſneſs.) This that I ſay of the Formaliſt is evident, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.8. with verſe 18, 19, 20. They were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant at their ſacrifices, but deeply guilty of Theft, Adultery, evil-ſpeaking, and falſe accuſations: with the ſame mouth did they bleſs God, or curſe or ſpeak evil of man made after the image of God, <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.9. ſo <hi>Jer.</hi> 7.4. They cry <hi>The Temple of the Lord. i. e</hi> duties, ſacrifices; but verſe 5, 6. <hi>They did not execute judgment between a man and his neighbour, they oppreſſed the ſtranger, the fatherleſs, and the widdow, they ſhed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent blood, &amp;c.</hi> ſo verſe 9. <hi>They did ſteal, murder, commit adultery, and ſwear
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:98196:46"/>
falſly.</hi> The like you may ſee <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.2. <hi>They ſeek me daily, and delight to know my waies, &amp;c.</hi> yea, verſe 3. They chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge God, and charge him as not having regard to their faſting, and afflicting their Souls: yet theſe, verſe 4. <hi>did faſt for ſtrife and debate, and to ſmite with with the fiſt of wickedneſs.</hi> See more of their failings towards their neighbour, verſe 6, 7, 9, 10. Where Gods cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling for ſuch duties at their hands, ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently intimates their defectiveneſs in them. Poſſibly ſome ſmaller acts of righteouſneſs or mercy they may doe; ſo did the Phariſees, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.23. <hi>They tithed Mint, Anniſe</hi> and <hi>Cummin, but the weightier points of the law, judgment, mercy, or faith,</hi> (that is, as ſome with good reaſon interpret, faithfulneſs in their dealings with men) theſe they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glected. Yea, by their rare device of <hi>Corban, i. e.</hi> a gift given to the Prieſt or Temple, that their Parents might be prayed for, diſoblige the child from that neceſſary duty of ſuccouring his neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitous Parents: <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.5.6. with <hi>Mark</hi> 7.11, 12. Thus making pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended piety towards God, a cloak for neglect of duty towards man: and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:98196:46"/>
this account how many Formaliſts are to be found amongſt us? are not many, that have ſet up Prayer and read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their Families, who frequent Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, and ſeem to be eminent in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as bad, yea much worſe in ſecond-Table-duties, then the prophaneſt? Who more griping and oppreſive? Who more ready to over-reach in Bargaining? To defraud or abridg their Miniſter of his due? So that (as to the buſineſs of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, and juſtice of people towards their Miniſter) we could rather deſire to be caſt upon a prophane, ſuperſtitious, ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant people, then amongſt knowing Formaliſts: Beſides, who more quarrel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome? fuller of ſtrife and debate? more apt to go to Law for trifles, then theſe? Can theſe things conſiſt with ſincertty? are they not plain evidences of a rotten heart, a meer Formaliſt? Surely ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity hath an equal reſpect to all God's Commandments, will not knowingly bank any; much leſs make obedience to one, a cloak of diſobedience to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Add one more briefly: The For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maliſt is regardleſs of his own heart: A ſtranger to that Duty <hi>Solomon</hi> preſſes,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:98196:47"/>
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 4.13. <hi>Keep thy heart above all keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> This is (if I may ſo ſpeak) the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Formalis Ratio,</hi> the Eſſence of Forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, that the heart is wanting in all he doth: he hath an eye to his Converſion, (as far as it is obvious to the eye of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) but lets his heart run at liberty. Now the ſincere Chriſtian's work is moſt within; his greateſt care is in weeding, dreſſing, keeping clean, watching over his own heart: he hath a wary eye to every entrance and out-going of the ſoul. Thus you ſee ſome rude draught of a Formaliſt: Judg your ſelves by theſe Characters; and, if you find cauſe, apply the Text and Doctrine to your own hearts; rectifie your miſtakes, and judg of your ſelves as the Word judges of you; it may do you good: for this is not a judgment of final deciſion, but of trial and diſcuſſion, which may bring you into the right way.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The fourth and laſt Uſe I ſhall make of the Doctrine, is Exhortation; in which, 1. A word to the Prophane, 2. To the Formaliſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:98196:47"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> The fourth and laſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of the point, <hi>viz.</hi> Exhortation: And firſt to the Prophane, That they will improve their hopes: Proſecuted, <hi>1.</hi> by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections. <hi>2.</hi> Encouraging Motives.</head>
               <p n="1">1. TO you that wallow in the mire of ſin, and drink the very dregs of iniquity; ſee your hopes, your poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, your probabilities for Heaven, and lay hold on them: poſſibly ſome of you may conceit your caſe hopeleſs and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate, but take not up ſuch ſad conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions: There is yet hopes in <hi>Iſrael</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this thing; ſay not then with the Eunuch and ſtranger, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.3. The Lord hath utterly ſeperated me from his people, <hi>Behold I am a dry tree:</hi> Nor with the Apoſtate Jews, <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.25. <hi>There is no hope, &amp;c.</hi> Deſpair will make you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate: 'Tis the Epicures language. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.32. <hi>Let us eat and drink, for to morrow we die: (q. d.)</hi> Let us take our fill of pleaſure and voluptuouſneſs here, we know not what our portion will be in another world; none are ſo obſtinately
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:98196:48"/>
wicked, as they that have hardned them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by deſpair. I have read of one, who after a firſt and ſecond relapſe from purpoſed and promiſed Reformation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the third time viſited with ſickneſs, ſent for his Miniſter, who minding him of his former promiſes and failings in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance, aggravating his ſin upon him, he told him, that except he did ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily and ſeriouſly repent, and put away his Harlot (who was then in his houſe) there was no hope of his Salvation. His reply was, Say you ſo; can I not be ſaved except I put her away? Then I will do as well as I can while I live; ſo calling for Wine, Cards, and that Woman, he ſpent his time (which was but three or four days) in mirth and pleaſure, and ſo in a moment went down into the grave. Oh take heed of bringing your ſelves to this paſs! That Scripture is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, <hi>Job</hi> 15.21, 24. <hi>A doleful ſound is in his ears, Trouble and anguiſh ſhall make him afraid.</hi> Here's his deſpair, or horror of Conſcience: ſee the effect of it, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 25, 26. <hi>He ſtretcheth out his hand againſt God, and ſtrengthneth himſelf againſt the Almighty: he runneth upon him, even on his neck, upon the thick boſſes of his buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers.</hi>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:98196:48"/>
Some wild Beaſts, when hunted to a ſtand, will turn again, and fly in your face: So do ſinners, when grown deſperate, even fly in the face of God himſelf. 'Tis the Devils ordinary way, when he hath drawn men into ſin, and kept them in it as long as he can, when they begin to think of turning, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade them there is no hope. Oh but conſider the Text, poſſibly thy caſe may be more hopeful then many a one that paſſes in the world for a ſincere Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an: yet the door is open, the Golden Scepter is held out; thy caſe is not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate; make it not ſo by going on ſtill in thy wickedneſs: Preſumption begins obduration, but deſpair heightens and compleats it. If once thou drink in this deadly concluſion, That there is no poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility of Salvation for thee; thou wilt then bid defiance to God: This made one ſhoot his darts againſt Heaven; ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther throw up handfuls of his own blood, crying out <hi>Viciſti Galilaea,</hi> O <hi>Galilean,</hi> thou haſt overcome: A third, wiſh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf above God, that he might be able to grapple with him; and a fourth lay vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent hands upon himſelf, and become his own Executioner. This is it that makes
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:98196:49"/>
the Devil a Devil, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.19. <hi>He believes and trembles:</hi> 'Tis a Hell worſe then Hell it ſelf: See therefore, and lay hold on thy opportunity: Publicans and Harlots, (ſaith the Text) go into the Kingdom of God, art thou worſe? 'Twas a cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing word to poor blind <hi>Bartimeus,</hi> Mar. 10.49. <hi>Be of good comfort, riſe, he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth thee.</hi> The ſame I may ſay to you, he came to call ſinners (and are not you ſuch) to repentance: Oh that you would now imitate that poor blind man, who <hi>V.</hi> 50. caſt away his Garment, roſe and came to Jeſus, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.43. with 47, 48. See how the Gentiles rejoyced and flockt in, when God vouchſafes them an invitation. Poor ſouls! They thought God had caſt them off, and not reſerved ſuch a bleſſing for them; therefore they are even raviſhed with the glad tidings, and become as Corn fully ripe, that ſhakes into the hand of the Reaper; or as mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low fruits, dropping into the mouth of him that gathers them: Oh that this diſcovery of the like hopes for you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane ſinners, might have the like opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon you! Oh that I could hear ſome poor ſoul pouring out ſuch brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things as theſe! What? Is there hopes
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:98196:49"/>
for me? for me an old Drunkard, an unclean wretch, <hi>&amp;c?</hi> Will Chriſt vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to give me a call, an invitation? Is it poſſible, that I that have ſpent my choice time, exhauſted my beſt Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> upon ſin, ſhould yet be in a poſſibility of Heaven? Is it thy plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, dear Saviour, to beſtow thy Blood and Merits, thy Grace and Spirit; yea, an heavenly Inheritance, a Crown of Glory on ſuch a dead dog as I am? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly though none could have leſs hope, yet none hath more need then I; ſince there is a peradventure, I will go in; if I pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, I periſh: Oh take the Prophets Counſel, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.7. <hi>Let the wicked for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake his way, and the unrighteous man his thoughts; and let him return unto the Lord, and he will have mercy upon him, and to our God, for he will abundantly pardon.</hi> Give me leave to ſub-join two or three words of Direction, and as many of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Come within the call of Chriſt; lie at the <hi>Betheſda</hi> of Ordinances; put your ſelves under the Phyſicians hands, if you will be cured: <hi>Faith comes by hearing, Rom.</hi> 10.17. Miſs not an opportunity; you know not when the Spirit will blow,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:98196:50"/>
or the Angel deſcend to move theſe wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: Though God hath called ſome from the Ale-bench, Tavern, Stews, Receit of Cuſtom; yet it is not to be preſum'd God will do ſo; 'tis out of Gods ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary road. Thoſe whom Chriſt cured, or called, were ſuch ordinarily as were in his way: So the ten Lepers, <hi>Luke</hi> 17.12. The blind man, <hi>Luke</hi> 18.35. The wounded man lay in the way betwixt <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rico</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Zacheus</hi> got into the Sycamore-tree where Chriſt was to paſs by, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.4, 5. and he hears that glad tidings, <hi>Come down Zacheus,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zek</hi> 16.6. <hi>When I paſſed by thee—I ſaid unto thee, live:</hi> 'Tis good to be where Chriſt may paſs by us, and that is in his Church, amongſt his people; for his walk is in the midſt of the ſeven golden Candleſticks, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.1. <hi>Wiſdom cries with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, ſhe uttereth her voice in the ſtreets; ſhe cryeth in the chief place of concourſe, &amp;c. Prov.</hi> 1.20— What hope maiſt thou conceive if thou waiteſt at her Gates, and watcheſt daily at the poſts of her doors, ſince ſuch are pronounced bleſſed, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.34? Some have been caught in the net before they were aware, (a happy catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing!) yea, when they came to catch,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:98196:50"/>
carp and deride: What hope maiſt thou have, if thou wilt conſtantly and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiouſly wait upon God in his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Call upon Chriſt; caſt thy ſelf at his feet, with the Lepers, and the blind man, <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.41. <hi>Lord, that I might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive my ſight.</hi> Learn the Publicans po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.13. <hi>Lord be merciful to me a ſinner.</hi> Take the Apoſtles coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel to <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> Act. 8.22. <hi>Pray that the thoughts of thy heart may be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given thee:</hi> ſuch prayers, (whatever ſome ſay) ſhall not be rejected; elſe why doth the Holy Ghoſt direct to the uſe of them? Chriſt hath taught thee importunity, <hi>Luke</hi> 18.1-8. Put his Leſſon in practice; beg pardon and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification: ſay to Chriſt, Lord ſpread thy ſpirit over me, ſince thou art become a near kinſman: Beg Sanctification; Lord here's a filthy heart, O cleanſe it; a hard heart, O mollifie it; a dead heart, O quicken it: Plead ſuch free Promiſes as that, and put them in ſuit, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.26. <hi>Take, Lord, the ſtone out of my heart, and give me an heart of fleſh: ſprinkle clean water upon me, &amp;c.</hi> Take up <hi>Ephraim's</hi> words, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.18. <hi>Turn thou me, and
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:98196:51"/>
I ſhall be turned, for thou art the Lord my God;</hi> And <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14.1, 2. Plead the examples of ſuch as thou art, whoſe converſion is recorded for thy encouragement; <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalen, Zacheus, Paul:</hi> ſee that ſweet Scripture, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15, 16. <hi>How be it, for this cauſe I obtained mercy, that in me firſt Jeſus Chriſt might ſhew forth all long-ſuffering, for a pattern to them which ſhould hereafter believe on him to life everlaſting.</hi> Caſt thy ſelf upon him, in confidence of that word, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.37. <hi>Him that cometh unto me, I will in no wiſe caſt off:</hi> Plead as the ſervants of <hi>Benhadab,</hi> 1 King. 20.31. <hi>I have heard the God of Iſrael is a merciful God:</hi> A meer peradventure ſhould be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to an undone Creature, as it was to the four Lepers, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 7.8. much more when thou haſt ſuch invitations and encouragements to allure thee to come in.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Caſt away thy tranſgreſſions, Ezek.</hi> 18.31. Thou canſt not be ſaved in them, but from them thou maiſt: This is the good old way wherein onely thou ſhalt find reſt for thy ſoul. <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.16. This doctrine will abide the fire, when all the wood, hay and ſtubble of novel and unſcriptural ſpeculations, will be burnt:
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:98196:51"/>
'Tis Chriſt's own Doctrine, <hi>Luke</hi> 13.3, 5. Away then with thy lewd compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, exceſs, revellings; put away thoſe works of the fleſh, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22. elſe take no comfort in all: I have ſaid, read o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the examples of all thoſe that were ſaved, eſpecially ſuch prophane ones as thy ſelf: Was not this valley of <hi>Achor,</hi> bitter Repentance, their door of hope: 'Tis not <hi>Paul</hi> the Perſecutor, but <hi>Paul</hi> the Penitent, the faithful Apoſtle, that is in Heaven: Not <hi>Zacheus</hi> the Oppreſſor, but <hi>Zacheus</hi> the Reſtorer: Not <hi>Magda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len</hi> the Harlot, but <hi>Magdalen</hi> the Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent; weeping <hi>Magdalen,</hi> waſhing Chriſt's feet with her tears, and wiping them with the hairs of her head: And what is there in any ſin, that hopes of future glory ſhould not make thee willing to part with it? Is the Favour of God? Are the Conſolations of the Spirit? The Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges of the Saints? Is Heaven, and Glory, and the eternal fruition of the Beatifical Viſion, ſo contemptible, that they cannot out-bid one baſe luſt? Are the pleaſures of ſin for a ſeaſon, better then the eternal recompence of reward? Are devouring flames, everlaſting burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings ſuch light matters, ſo eaſie to be
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:98196:52"/>
endured, that for the enjoyment of ſome worldly delight or contentment, perhaps for ſome ſin that hath in it neither pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit nor pleaſure, (ſuch as ſwearing is) you ſhould plunge your ſelves into them irrecoverably? Do you believe thoſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal things, or no? If not, Why do you come to hear? Why do you not declare your ſelves profeſſed Atheiſts, and lay aſide all Profeſſion of Religion? Why do you not take your fill of carnal pleaſures? But if you do believe them, (as I know you will profeſs you do) why do you not put away your abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? Why do you not fly from the wrath to come, by bringing forth fruits meet for Repentance? Will you yet ſay, my caſe is hopeleſs, I have ſinned away my opportunities? Look once again into the Text, ſee who the perſons are; Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licans, and Harlots: What their privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg is; they go into the Kingdom of God: To whom they are preferred, as to their hopes of Salvation; the Moral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Righteous, the Formal Profeſſor, you may (if you will take the courſe preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed) ſtep into Heaven before them: But that I may leave you without ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in this particular, take theſe two
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:98196:52"/>
conſiderations further along with you.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Will not God, think you, be moſt ready to do that which beſt pleaſes, and moſt honours him? and what's that but pardoning the Penitent, embracing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning Prodigals? Do you queſtion this? A great part of Scripture, yea, the very ſcope of the Goſpel may convince you. Read <hi>Jer.</hi> 9.24. <hi>Mich.</hi> 7.18. <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od.</hi> 34.6, 7. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.7. <hi>Joel</hi> 2.12, 13— Will you believe God upon his word? he hath told you, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.32. that he hath no pleaſure in the death of him that dieth: will you have his Oath? <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.11. <hi>As I live, ſaith the Lord God, I have no pleaſure in the death of the wicked, but that the wicked turn from his way and live;</hi> [herein he hath pleaſure:] <hi>turn ye, turn ye from your evil ways,</hi> &amp;c. If nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Word nor Oath will ſerve, yet I hope his Actings, and gracious Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions towards the ſons of Men, towards your ſelves, may paſs for a Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Had God delighted in the Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; yea, had he not had unſpeakably more delight in the ſalvation of poor ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, would he have ſent his Son? Would he have publiſhed the Goſpel? Would he wait, and beſeech, and ſo patheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:98196:53"/>
beg your ſouls? 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19. And for thy own caſe, could not God have thrown thee into Hell ſo ſoon as thou waſt born, if that had pleaſed him? Would he have been at ſo much coſt and pains with thee? Or if thou now return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, will he not accept thee; yea, meet thee while yet afar off, fall upon thy neck, and kiſs thee, who hath been ſo long waiting that he might be graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous unto thee? And then for the honour of God; 'tis true, he can get it in thy deſtruction, but he had rather thou wouldeſt give it him in thy Salvation: Such is his Philanthropy, and love to man, that he eſteems that his greateſt honour, which conſiſts with his creatures greateſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs. Let me ſpeak a ſerious word; Which do you think will make the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er melody in God's Ear? whether the eternal howlings and yellings of the damned, blaſpheming, and tearing his Name in pieces; or the inceſſant Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings and Hallelujahs of glorified Saints, ſinging Praiſes to him that ſits upon the Throne, and to the Lamb for ever and ever? And for you to whom I am ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing [Prophane ſinners] How ſingularly pleaſing will it be to God? How de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:98196:53"/>
to the Angels, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to entertain you into their heavenly ſociety? (to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain you, I ſay, not ſuch as now you are, but waſht in the blood of the Lamb, cloath'd with white linnen, which is the Righteouſneſs of the Saints) read, and read again thoſe three Parables of the Prodigal ſon, the loſt groat, and loſt Sheep, <hi>Luke</hi> 18. They tell you, there is more joy in Heaven over one ſinner that repenteth, then over ninety and nine juſt perſons that need no repentance; and for the glory of God, he will both get more by you, (for the Phyſician's skill is commended by the deſperateneſs of the diſeaſe he cures) and you wil (at leaſt endeavour) give him more then others: If we may imagine an holy ſtrife and emula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion amongſt the glorified Saints, to excel each other in praiſing God; ſurely they that have exceeded others in ſinning here, will in ſinging hereafter: they to whom moſt is forgiven, will love moſt, admire moſt, and labour to riſe higheſt in their praiſes: So that this may be helpful a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any d ſcouraging fears of being rejected: 'Tis ſingularly pleaſing and honouring to God, that you ſhould come in; you cannot ſuppoſe God unwilling
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:98196:54"/>
to receive you upon your ſerious return, but you ſuppoſe him alſo falſe in his word, his oath; deceitful in his actings, and unfaithful to the great intereſt of his own glory: all which is no leſs then blaſphemy to imagine.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Will Jeſus Chriſt, think you, be more willing that his blood ſhould be ſpilt, and the great end of his underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king fruſtrate (as to you) in your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, then accompliſhed in your ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation? Did he take all that pains, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo ſuch a ſhameful and ignominious death, the wrath of God, the terrors of Hell, to ſave poor loſt ſouls? and now all is done, and ready, nothing wanting but your conſent and application; And can you imagine, that he will rather loſe all, then freely beſtow what he hath ſo dearly purchaſed? True, he is not ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digal of his blood and merits as to throw them away upon thoſe that neither ſet their need of them, nor will thank him for them; but when you are ſenſible of your neceſſity, and humbly ſue to him for an intereſt in them, and caſt your ſelves upon him, do you think he will caſt you off? Hath he done the painful part, and will he not much more do the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:98196:54"/>
pleaſant part of the work? Will it not be abundant ſatisfaction to ſee the fruit of the travel of his ſoul, in the Converſion and Salvation of yours? O with what contentment and complacency will Chriſt embrace you? Welcome poor Prodigal, loſt, weary, heavy-laden ſoul; now it repents me not of all my toil and travel: 'tis enough that thou wilt accept what I have done and ſuffered for thee; I freely give thee my Blood to juſtifie thee, my Merit to procure thy acceptance with the Father; my Grace to ſanctifie thee, my Spirit to ſeal thee to the day of Redemption; yea, Heaven it ſelf for thine Inheritance: mine it is by purchaſe, and on thee I beſtow it; I expect nothing but thy ingenious accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and grateful obedience: Oh, you cannot more diſgrage the wiſdom or mercy of Chriſt, then to imagine him unwilling to beſtow himſelf, and all he hath done, upon thoſe that humbly beg it, in the deep ſenſe of their own neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity: ſo that let not the vileſt wretch, the prophaneſt ſinner in the Congregation, ſtand off upon ſuppoſition that God will not accept him, or that Chriſt will caſt him off: You ſee in the Text, who were
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:98196:55"/>
the chief materials of that ſtately Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick, the Chuch, when Chriſt and his Apoſtles were the builders, even Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans and Harlots, ſinners, ſuch as your ſelves are: With whom did Chriſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe? Whom came he to call? Who were they moſt commonly embraced by him, but ſuch? Nay, ſuch were not onely ſtones in the building, but Maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>builders, even <hi>Paul</hi> (though a Phariſee yet) in his own account, a Perſecutor, a Blaſphemer, Injurious, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.12. If you want not hearts, you want no hopes for Heaven. All this I have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, not in the leaſt to ſtrengthen your hands in wickedneſs, (Woe to him that ſhall ſo turn this grace of God into wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſs) but to remove that ſcruple which poſſibly may keep ſome at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from Chriſt; nor would I be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood as encouraging any to delay their turning to God, preſuming upon acceptance at laſt gaſp. Remember that of <hi>Auſtin, Qui dat poenitenti gratiam, non ſemper dat peccanti poenitentiam:</hi> He that gives pardon to the Penitent, doth not always give Repentance to the Sinner. Come then, Prophane Sinner, come ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily, ſeriouſly, humbly, and ſelf-deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:98196:55"/>
to Chriſt, and I promiſe thee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance; Make good the Text, Step into Heaven, and lay hold on Eternal Life before the proud Formaliſt. Then, though ſuch as they diſpiſe thee, God will accept, and prefer thee before them: Then, however filthy and polluted thou art, thou ſhalt be waſht in the Lambs blood, cloath'd with his Righteouſneſs, made comely with his comelineſs, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into that bleſſed ſociety, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.22, 23, 24. there to continue to all Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> The ſecond branch of Exhortation, <hi>viz.</hi> to the Formal Hypocrite, to haſten out of his dangerous condition; urged by divers Motives.</head>
               <p n="2">2. ANd now I turn to you the other ſubjects of my Text, Formal Chriſtians, who are painted Sepulchres, Graves that appear not, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.44. I have endeavoured to work upon the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers hopes, I ſhall now endeavour to work upon your fears: your condition, you ſee, is ſad and deplorable, yet not
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:98196:56"/>
deſperate: Have you not often in your thoughts (and it may be in your ſpeeches) paſſed a ſad doom upon the prophane? When you have heard them ſwearing, and blaſpheming the Name of God, imbru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their tongues in the blood and wounds of Chriſt, when you have ſeen them wallowing in their drunkenneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> have you not thought, O I would not be in that mans condition for all the world? yet by what hath been ſaid, you ſee your ſtate in ſome reſpect worſe then theirs; that there is a greater likelihood of their ſalvation, then of yours: What remains then, but that you turn your eyes inward, and take up the ſame thoughts concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your ſelves, which formerly you have had of them? you ſee what thoughts our Saviour had of ſuch as you are, <hi>Luke</hi> 18.9-14. there he tells you that a poor penitent Publican is rather juſtified (and conſequently ſaved) then proud ſelf-juſtifying Phariſees: in all his Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, What do ſuch as you hear, but woe, woe, as <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.13—<hi>end?</hi> when a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken-hearted <hi>Magdalen</hi> hears a ſweet word, <hi>Luke</hi> 7.48. <hi>Thy ſins are forgiven: Zacheus</hi> a gracious call, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.6, 9. <hi>Come down Zacheus, this day is ſalvation
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:98196:56"/>
come to thy houſe, foraſmuch as he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo is the Son of Abraham:</hi> and generally, weary, heavy-laden ſinners have a loving invitation, <hi>Math.</hi> 11.28. <hi>Come unto me all ye that labour and are heavy laden,</hi> backt with a ſweet promiſe, <hi>I will give you reſt.</hi> Oh then, let fall thoſe plumes of pride which have been lifted up ſo much above others; glory not in your ſpecious formalities and outſide clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs: <hi>That which is highly eſteemed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men, is abomination in the ſight of God. Luke</hi> 16.15. Bear not your ſelves high upon your parts, morality, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal performances, while there are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven abominations in your hearts, <hi>Prov.</hi> 26.25. Think not that your credit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men will beſtead you before the all-knowing God. But haſten out of your woful ſtate; learn that firſt and hardeſt leſſon of Chriſtianity, ſelf-denyal: labour to get what yet you want, a heart deeply humbled for ſin, an abſolute diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim of ſelf-righteouſneſs, and ſubmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the righteouſneſs of Chriſt, and Truth in the inward parts. Something I ſhall add by way of motive, and then directions.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Will it not grieve thee to the heart
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:98196:57"/>
to have loſt ſo many duties, prayers, days of hearing; faſting, thankſgiving? It may be many tears and ſighs, yea ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſcoffs, reproaches and injuries ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered for thy profeſſion. Let me take up the Apoſtles words, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.4. <hi>Have you ſuffered ſo many things in vain, if they be yet in vain?</hi> Will it not cut thee to the heart, to be ſeparated from that ſociety in heaven, with which thou haſt aſſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated here on earth? That, that which hath helpt others to heaven, ſhould ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidentally plunge thee deeper into hell? That thou haſt done and ſuffered more then many a one in glory, for the name and profeſſion of Chriſt, and all loſt? Loſt, 1. As to any acceptance with God here. 2. As to any advantage to thy ſelf hereafter: How will it repent thee of what thou haſt done and ſuffered in the profeſſion of Rel gion? how wilt thou wiſh that thou hadſt joined with the prophane crew? that thou hadſt never had thoſe gifts, made that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, done thoſe duties, which ſhall be (not only loſt as to any benefit of thy ſelf, but) as ſo many weights to preſs thee deeper into hell; Stings in thy tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and brands to increaſe the flame,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:98196:57"/>
and ſhall ſtand uncancelled, as ſo many dreadful Items in God's Book of remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, rendring thy account more hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy? Oh, will it not grieve you, when o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have ſworn, and drunk, and whor'd themſelves into Hell, that thou haſt hear'd, and pray'd, and faſted thy ſelf thither? (pardon the harſhneſs of the expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I mean by an ill management of thoſe duties) when others are damned for prophaneneſs, thou for thy (hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critical) profeſſion? others for their ſins, thou for thy (feigned) ſervices? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.19. If a Chriſtian hath hope onely in this life, he is of all men moſt miſerable: the reaſon is, becauſe they deny themſelves of worldly content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, expoſe themſelves to continual croſſes and vexations, in expectation of future glory, which, if they miſs of, they are every way miſerable. This is thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition: further, will it not grieve thee to be thruſt into Hell with that company which here thou abhorredſt? to be turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out with the workers of Iniquity, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 125. <hi>laſt.</hi> Nay, to have a hotter Hell then they? All this perhaps may ſound harſh in your ears, and you may ſuppoſe them to be but the Hyperbolical expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:98196:58"/>
of an Orator, declaiming againſt this ſin, or the over-heated eructations of miſtaken Zeal, and miſguided Paſſion: No, my Brethren, they are the words of Truth and ſoberneſs: The greater ſin ſhall have the greater puniſhment, (that's a known and granted maxime:) Now thy ſins are greater then many (I will not ſay then any) prophane perſon's: Is not contempt of Chriſt, and ſetting light by him, ſetting up your own Righteouſneſs in oppoſition to his, trampling upon his precious blood, a greater ſin then Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Drunkenneſs, <hi>&amp;c?</hi> Is it not Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion at the height, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.3.—have not ſubmitted themſelves unto (<hi>i. e.</hi> have rebelled againſt) the Righteouſneſs of God? Hereby you evacuate the ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Chriſt, expunge the Goſpel, and charge Chriſt with an unneceſſary un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking, yea, with ſelf-murder. Trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble then at the ſight of your condition. Truly, when I look on a Formaliſt, and conſider what pains he takes; his conſtancy in Hearing, Prayer, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther duties; when I look upon his almoſt ſpotleſs and unblameable converſation; me thinks 'tis pity ſuch ſhould be thrown into Hel: But when I conſider that pride &amp;
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:98196:58"/>
oppoſition to Chriſt lies at the root of all this; when I ſee him ſtrutting in his own rags, and will not be beholden to Chriſt; then me thinks the greateſt ſeverity as lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle enough, and the hotteſt corner in Hell cool enough to puniſh his deſperate mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Oh to ſlight the love of Chriſt, to make void his ſufferings, to ex-authorize him of his Mediatory office, how great a ſin is it, and how great puniſhment doth it deſerve? But I am almoſt digreſſed from that which I propounded. Well, if thou wilt not loſe the work which thou haſt wrought, 2 <hi>Joh.</hi> 8. if thou wilt not loſe thy duties, or be a loſer by them, Get out of this condition.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Will it not grieve thee to ſee Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licans and Harlots admitted into Heaven, and thy ſelf caſt out? See <hi>Matth.</hi> 8.11, 12. <hi>Many ſhall come from the Eaſt, and Weſt, and ſhall ſit down,</hi> &amp;c— But the Children of the Kingdom (the formal Jews) ſhall be caſt out into utter dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>There</hi> ('tis emphatical) <hi>there ſhall he weeping, and gnaſhing of teeth.</hi> Poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly thou liveſt amongſt a company of prophane Neighbours; and when thou neareſt ſome curſing and ſwearing, ſeeſt others prophaning the Lord's Day; ſome
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:98196:59"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:98196:59"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:98196:60"/>
Drunkards, others unclean and debau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in their lives; all of them ſcoffing at God, and Holineſs, which thou pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſeſt: thou bleſſeſt thy ſelf, and ſayeſt in thy heart (and not without good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) as <hi>Luk.</hi> 8.11. <hi>God, I thank thee, that I am not as other men are, &amp;c.</hi> But what if ſome of theſe, upon Repentance, ſtep before thee into Glory? What if thou ſeeſt hereafter ſome of theſe in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham's</hi> boſom, and thy ſelf in a Lake of brimſtone? What if theſe, waſht in the blood of the Lamb, cloath'd in the long white Robe, ſtand amongſt the ſheep at Chriſt's right hand, when thou in the filthy, ſtained rags of thy unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous righteouſneſs, ſhalt be thruſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Goats on his left hand; and when they hear, <hi>Come ye Bleſſed, &amp;c.</hi> thou hear, <hi>Go ye Curſed?</hi> Will not this even rend aſunder thy heart-ſtrings, and fill thy ſoul with unſpeakable hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror and conſternation? Thus doubtleſs it will be if thou live and die in thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. Oh that I could provoke you to jealouſie! as God threatens to do, and did provoke the Jews by the converſion of the Gentiles, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.21. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.11. One day, doubtleſs, you will be
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:98196:60"/>
provoked to a ſinful and malicious jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie at th s ſight; but I had rather now pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke you to a vertuous and holy jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, ſuch as might rouze you out of your Formality, and make you altogether Chriſtians. The Jews were never more incenſed, then when they were told God had rejected them, and embraced the Gentiles, <hi>Act.</hi> 22.21, 22. They gave him audience to that word, and then lift up their voices, and ſaid, <hi>Away with ſuch a fellow from the Earth, for it is not fit that he ſhould live.</hi> The elder Son grows ſullen and envious at his Prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal brothers entertainment and welcome, <hi>Luk.</hi> 15.28, 29. 'Tis not this ſinful envy that I would excite in you; but an holy jealouſie, fear, emulation; leſt ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane ones ſhould get before you into the Kingdom of God: If ſuch a ſight would be (as needs it muſt be) grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous and tormenting; endeavour now to prevent it by a timely eſcape from Formality; otherwiſe I ſhall ſay,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Averroes</hi> a Mahu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met n.</note> as the Heathen Philoſopher, who ſeeing the Chriſtians eat their pretended God, cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out, <hi>Sit anima mea cum Philoſophis;</hi> ſo I, <hi>Sit anima mea cum prophanis, (ſcil. penitentibus:</hi>) I had rather be a penitent
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:98196:61"/>
Thief, then a proud Formaliſt or Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciary.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thou never kneweſt, nor ſhalt know the real comforts of Chriſtianity, while thou continueſt in Formality: a painted Chriſtian hath but imaginary comforts; the Hypocrite hath but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.2, 5. a Hypocrites reward, proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate to his ſervice: Sincerity, as it ſhall onely wear the Crown hereafter, ſo it onely enjoyeth true ſolid conſolation here: The joy of the Holy Ghoſt is their priviledg, who are made partakers of the Holy Ghoſt, not in his common gifts, but ſaving graces: The true waters of conſolation are drawn out of thoſe wells of ſalvation, the ſenſe of God's ſpecial love ſhed abroad in the heart, the blood of Chriſt ſprinkled upon the conſcience, and the ſanctifying ſpirit of God, firſt working, and then ſhining upon his own work: He that is a ſtranger to theſe, is a ſtranger to true joy, and who but the ſincere Chriſtian hath theſe things? The ſtream can neither riſe higher, nor continue longer then the fountain whence it ariſes; and what is the fountain of a Formaliſts comfort, but his own ſpotted righteouſneſs, and ſorry performances?
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:98196:61"/>
the web wherewith he covers himſelf is ſpun out of his own bowels, and this can neither afford him warmth, nor long en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure: The ſparks wherewith he encom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſeth himſelf, are but from a fire of his own kindling; all the light and warmth he hath, is thence; and what then can his portion be, but at laſt to lie down in ſorrow? <hi>Iſ.</hi> 50.11. When he is brought to the King of terrors, his confidence ſhall be rooted out of his tabernale, <hi>Job</hi> 18.14. His comfort is but a land-flood, violent, but not laſting. 'Tis evident; for,</p>
               <p n="1">1. All true comfort flows from Chriſt, from a ſaving intereſt in him, and recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation with God by him: this the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maliſt hath not; he never drunk of that rock, but onely out of the muddy pud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles of his own polluted duties, which have nothing but filth and gravel at the bottom.</p>
               <p n="2">2. True Conſolation is the conſequent of ſound Humiliation (to which he is a ſtranger) <hi>Pſal.</hi> 126.5, 6. <hi>They that ſow in tears, ſhall reap in joy, &amp;c. Iſa.</hi> 66.10. There ſeems to be ſomething to purpoſe intimated in that, <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.10. <hi>The heart knows his own bitterneſs, and the ſtranger
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:98196:62"/>
intermedleth not with his joy.</hi> Why may not the meaning be this, That as the heart hath its ſorrows that others know not, ſo its comforts alſo; and he that never knew the one, ſhall never taſte the other? however the thing is a Truth. The vapours of a truly hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled ſoul's tears, ſighs, ſorrows, exhaled, do afterwards come down in refreſhing dews, and ſhowers of conſolation. Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quors bottled up, increaſe their ſtrength and virtue: God bottles up the tears of his people, and theſe waters ſo bottled, are turned into wine of conſolation. But the Formaliſt never knew how to weep for ſin, as ſin; he is a ſtranger to thoſe Evangelical meltings, and therefore can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not have thoſe reviving cordials of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</p>
               <p n="3">3. True comfort is the fruit of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience pacified, purified, ſanctified: 2 <hi>Cor</hi> 1.12. This is (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) our exultation, the Teſtimony of a good Conſcience, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſuch is not the Formaliſt's Conſcience; ſilent and peaceable it may be, not pacified; for that's onely by the blood of ſprinkling: it may bring in an abſolving verdict, but it's upon miſtake, which will be rectified by the ſupreme
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:98196:62"/>
Judg at the laſt day. Well then: Wouldſt thou drink the pure wine of Conſolation? Wouldſt thou taſte of the hidden Manna? Have the new Name? The white ſtone? Get out of thy Formality; Be that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, which now thou woudſt be account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and deſireſt to be found at laſt, A ſincere Chriſtian.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Let this conſideration drive thee out of thy Formality: He that is no more then form, will, very probably, ere long, become leſs then form: Formality is but a water-colour, not laid in the oil of grace, not dried in the grain of Chriſt's blood, and therefore will fade: it will either wear off in time, or waſh off with the waters of affliction. The Stage-Player who onely bears the perſon of a Prince; when his part is acted, and the Comedy ended, puts off his habit, and is but what he was before: The Forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt doth but perſonate and repreſent the Chriſtian, and this will not always continue, <hi>Job</hi> 27.10. Will the Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite delight himſelf in the Almighty? will he always call upon God? He will not: Artificial Chriſtians will be but Temporaries: Such were <hi>Judas, Demas, Julian:</hi> nor wilt thou onely loſe what
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:98196:63"/>
thou ſeemeſt to have, but become worſe: The ſalt that hath loſt its ſavour, makes the very ground it is caſt upon, barren. The counterfeit friends of Religion, have often proved her moſt embittered Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. <hi>Julian's</hi> little finger (who once profeſſed Chriſtianity) was heavier then the loins of the other perſecuting Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors: rottenneſs in profeſſion, often turns into ranchor and malice againſt it. Had ſome of the Apoſtates of this age been told, while they made profeſſion of the Truth, that they ſhould become revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of Miniſters, contemners of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, violent Perſecutors of that way they then profeſſed; that they ſhould be ready to pull out the eyes of thoſe, for whom they ſeem'd willing even to pull out their own: would they not have been ready to ſay with <hi>Hazael,</hi> 2 King. 8.13. <hi>Is thy ſervant a dog, that he ſhould do this great thing?</hi> Yet this is the fruit of Formality and Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie: well, if you would ſtand, and keep your ſtation, be more then form. They that are but Comets will fall: and he that begins in Hypocriſie, will end in Apoſtaſie: if thou haſt onely a name to live, it will ere long appear that
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:98196:63"/>
thou art indeed dead: a meer name will not long preſerve a man from <hi>rottenneſs</hi> and <hi>putrefaction:</hi> Formality will ſhrink in the wetting; the fire will diſcover who are but droſs, <hi>Luke</hi> 8.13. Times of perſecution, are times of falling off, to thoſe that are not truly fixed: whence are all thoſe ſad falls in our days but from want of Truth in the inward parts? <hi>Pſ.</hi> 37.31. <hi>The Law of the Lord is in his heart; none of his ſteps ſhall ſlide:</hi> The Forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt hath the Law only in his head, and on his tongue; this is not enough to keep him from falling. And oh think what a Diſcredit it will be to turn Apoſtate, Renegado: How will God and man ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor thee? good men becauſe thou art not what thou once ſeemedſt to be; bad men, becauſe thou didſt once ſeem to be good: get therefore out of this condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which will have ſo ſad an iſſue.</p>
               <p n="5">5. But ſuppoſe thou mayeſt hold out, it will be bitterneſs in the end; however thou mayſt eſcape the diſcredit and ſhame of Apoſtaſie here, thou canſt not eſcape the danger and damnation of thy Formality hereafter. The Text tells thee, that <hi>Publicans</hi> and <hi>Harlots</hi> go before thee into the Kingdome of Heaven; but as
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:98196:64"/>
they go, not before, but upon repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; ſo neither ſhalt thou follow after, but upon the ſame condition. Formali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty will as certainly damn thee as any other ſin; and thruſt you as deep into hell, as almoſt any other, and what com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort will it be, that thou haſt left a good name behind thee, that thou didſt live and die under the repute of a ſincere Chriſtian? the miſtaken commendations of ſurviving Chriſtians, will be but a poor allay to the ſcorching flames of hell: yea, it will aggravate thy torment to think, (as probably thou mayeſt think) Now ſome are ſpeaking and hoping well concerning me on earth, while I am howling and yelling in theſe flames. 'Tis ſome addition to a mans grief under extremity of pain or ſickneſs, to be judg'd by others in a better ſtate then indeed he is: To be canonized on earth is but ſorry comfort to him that is condemned in hell! what good did the honours that were done to <hi>Nero,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sueton.</note> at, and after his death, do to him; though as the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian tells us, <hi>Non defuerunt qui Neronent vernis aeſtiviſque coloribus ornarent:</hi> There wanted not ſome to ſtrow his curſed grave with the flowers of the ſpring:
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:98196:64"/>
                  <hi>Salvian</hi> (as I find him quoted) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains, that <hi>Multorum corpora ſplendent in ſepulchris quorum, animae ardent in Gehemâ.</hi> Some were rendred glorious at their fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals, whoſe miſerable ſouls were fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in hell: a poor recompenſe! this is no allay, but is, or would be an aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of their torment, if they knew it. 'Tis ſtoried of one preaching at the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral of a ſuppoſed religious man, and giving him large commendations, a voice was heard, ſaying, <hi>Mortuus ſum, judicatus ſum, condemnatus ſum:</hi> for the truth of the ſtory, I ſhall leave it to your own diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whether to believe it or no; the moral may be good that damned ſouls take little delight in the commendations of Survi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors; for a man that takes a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience with him; and whoſe good works follow him, it is ſomething to leave a good name behind him, for <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.7. <hi>The memory of the juſt ſhall be bleſſed;</hi> but where the two former are wanting, the laſt will <hi>rot</hi> ſooner or later; the great day will rectifie all miſtakes in that kind. If we would have a name that might out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live that day, we muſt get out of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality, and come up to ſincerity, which is Goſpel-perfection.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:98196:65"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Helps or Directions to the formal Hypocrite, in order to his coming out of that condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and becoming a ſound and thorough Chriſtian.</head>
               <p>BUt that I may propound ſomething by way of Cure and Remedy, (for what is it to diſcover a diſeaſe, and leave the Patient in it?) Take theſe helps againſt it.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Direct. </seg>1</label> Get a convincing ſight (and humbling ſenſe of this ſin) ſight and ſenſe of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, is the great ſpur to put us upon ſeeking after remedy: the ſenſleſly ſick, will laugh in the face of the Phyſician; but he that feels his ſickneſs, will embrace the cure: and however, in outward ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladies it is not always neceſſary that the Patient be ſenſible in order to cure; yet in ſpiritual, the feeling of our diſtemper is not only a preparative to, but a good part of the Remedy. The will muſt concur to the Cure of Spiritual diſeaſes, in order to which, the underſtanding muſt be convinced. But becauſe it is one thing to ſee ſin, and another to feel it, I ſhall ſpeak to each ſeverally.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:98196:65"/>1. Then, that thou mayeſt have a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing ſight of this ſin, and that thy heart may be forced to acknowledg it, (beſides the Notes and Characters before laid down) make uſe of theſe two Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Be a narrow vigilant obſerver of thy own heart. The very eſſence of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality lies in this, That all is done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out heart or life. So that if thou find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thy heart ſtupid, ſenſleſs, without motion in duty, and this be thy conſtant frame: thence conclude thy ſelf a meer Formaliſt. Were I to deſcribe ſuch a one, I would in ſhort, call him, the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaſs of a Chriſtian, one that hath the outward lineaments, but wants the life and ſoul of a Chriſtian; that hath much of Religion in his head, and upon his tongue, but nothing of it in his heart: One that is moved and acted like a Pup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet or Engine, not from an inward prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, but by an external poiſe or impulſe. 'Tis true indeed, the beſt of Chriſtians have their dead and cold fits; but theſe, as they are not conſtant, ſo they are their grief and burden, the matter of their complaint and humiliation. If therefore thou art conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dead, and ſo far, as to be ſecure and ſenſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:98196:66"/>
in, and of thy deadneſs, this may faſten the conviction of this ſin upon thy heart.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Obſerve thy non-proficiency under Means. This is another evidence. A paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Tree or man is always in the ſame ſtate, but the living grows; the living Chriſtian thrives, and gets ground of corruption: Where there is a principle of Life, there will be growth. How did <hi>Nicodemus</hi> grow in Chriſtian courage? <hi>John</hi> 3.1, 2. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with <hi>John</hi> 7.50, 51. The ſmoaking Flax will become a flame, and the morning-glimpſe come on to a noon-day brightneſs. True, the Chriſtian is not alwayes ſenſible of his growth, nor a fit Judg of it. That of the Orator concerning growth in knowledg, may be fitly appli'd hither; As we ſee the ſhadow of a Dial to have gone, but ſee it not go; and the Herb or Graſs to have grown, but do not ſee it grow; ſo the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of knowledg, (and the ſame may be ſaid of Grace) becauſe it conſiſts of very ſmall additions, is ſeen only at ſome diſtance: Yet with theſe limitations, I may affirm, That every true Chriſtian is in a conſtant, thriving poſture.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That he grows downward (like Trees in Winter) when he ſeems to decay upward: he grows more humble, when he ſeems to be
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:98196:66"/>
leſs holy; and this is real growth. God in wiſdom ſuſpends his influences as to the growth of other Graces, that there may be a proportionable growth in that. Chriſtians, like the <hi>Athenian</hi> Students, the more they grow in Grace, the more out of conceit with themſelves: As they at their firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thither, arrogated the Name of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Wiſe men; then <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Lovers of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom: Afterwards <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Speakers of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. At laſt <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Ideots. So it is with Chriſtians.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That he grows more into hatred of ſin, when he ſeems to decay in ſtrength againſt it; when he feels corruption prevail, luſts predominant; he cryes out with the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.15. <hi>What I hate, that do I.</hi> And v. 24. <hi>O wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliver me from the body of this death?</hi> He more loaths ſin and himſelf, that he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conquer it; he abhors the very thoughts of it, and grows more impatient of its yoke.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That he grows in depth of Judgment, when he declines in height of Affection: poſſibly when young, he had more leaves and bloſſoms, ſtronger affections, and more ſerverous motions; but now is more ſober and ſolid. At firſt he was ſick of love;
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:98196:67"/>
now more rooted in love.</p>
               <p>But now it is otherwiſe with the Forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt; he experiences no ſuch growth, but the contrary; he goes backward, and not forward, <hi>Jer.</hi> 7.24. grows more proud and ſelf-confident; ſin grows leſs burdenſome, or more delightful to him; as he hath leſs ſtrength, ſo he hath leſs heart then former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to reſiſt ſin, or perform duty. Conſcience is in a conſumption, and he that would have ſtrain'd at a Gnat, can after ſome time ſwallow a Camel; he loſes his ſeeming love to, and ſavour of Religion. Obſerve then if it be thus with thee; for by theſe thou mayeſt diſcover thy Formality.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But it is not enough to get a convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing ſight of this ſin, <hi>i e.</hi> that thou art a Formaliſt, except thou haſt alſo an humb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſenſe of it; there's a great diſtance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the eye and heart; a man may clearly ſee that he is a ſinner, yet be little affected with it; the Drunkard, Swearer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but ſee their ſin, yet are far from feeling it: It muſt be therefore our endeavour, in order to the cure of this ſin, to get the heart affected, as well as the Judgment convinced: Sin muſt be our burden, elſe we ſhall never look out for eaſe: To this end therefore it muſt be thy endeavour to view this ſin in its
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:98196:67"/>
aggravations; to conſider, and dwell upon the conſideration of its hainouſneſs, till thy heart be preſſed with the weight of it. To help thee a little in this, take a few things of many.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is a ſin that turns the greateſt reality in the world into a meer ſhew and ſhadow: Religion is the greateſt reality; all we do in the World, beſides the work of Religion, is but a meer dream; Regeneration, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God, the Spiritual combat, the Life of Faith, Mortification of ſin, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> theſe are realities indeed: Now Formality turns all theſe into a naked, empty Profeſſion, a vain Theatrical ſhew; (as the Poetical Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Eccho, metamorphoſd from a real Virgin, to a meer Sound) as the <hi>Papiſts</hi> have turn'd the true Faſt, into a m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ck-faſt; Repentance and afflicting the ſoul, into laſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the Body, and Pilgrimages; the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Supper, into a dumb ſhew; and the whole Worſhip of God into a cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monious Enterlude: So the Formaliſt turns Prayer, Hearing, Sacraments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> into ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows; and is this a ſmall ſin, think you? Dwell upon this conſideration; how ſoon would Religion vaniſh into nothing, if there were not a few ſerious ſpirits to uphold it in the power of it? This eats out the kernel,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:98196:68"/>
the heart, the life of Religion. It was no leſs ſerious, then witty a diviſion which one gave of that Text, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Having a form of godlineſs</hi>—Here (ſaid he) you have, 1. The Body of Religion, <hi>viz.</hi> Form. 2. The Soul of Religion, <hi>viz.</hi> Power. 3. The death of Religion, and that is the ſeparation of the Soul from the Body, Power from Form. This is the effect of thy ſin, it murders Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is a mocking God to his very face; it's a lying to God, and will God endure it? What are your formal Petitions, Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Thankſgivings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but meer mockeries? Thou com'ſt to hear, but it is as they in <hi>Jer.</hi> 42.5, 6, 9. who when they received a Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage contrary to their deſigns, tell the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet to his face, that he lies; or as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.2. who were but as a people that did righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and forſook not the Ordinances of their God—Or as they are deſcribed in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.31, 32. The Prophet's Preaching was to them as a very lovely ſong of one that hath a pleaſant voice—<hi>They heard his words, but did them not:</hi> And what greater abuſe can be put upon God, then for men to come, and pretend a deſire to know his Will, yet to take no care of performing it? As to your prayers, I may invert that of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:98196:68"/>
14. <hi>Your underſtanding prayeth, but the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is unfruitful.</hi> Your approaches to the Lords Table, are no better than a <hi>Judas</hi>'s kiſs; nor can God take any more pleaſure in your approaches, then he did in the like ſervice of the <hi>Jews, Iſa.</hi> 1.12-15. &amp; 66.3 You do but complement with God, and that is no better then meer mockery: O think how wretched a thing it is, how highly diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing! your duties all of them, while you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in Formality, are ſo many jeers and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes put upon God.</p>
               <p n="3">3. By this ſin you put a cheat and falla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy upon your own ſouls; you mock God, but deceive your ſelves. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.3. <hi>If a man think himſelf to be ſomething when he is nothing,</hi> [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] <hi>he deceives himſelf,</hi> ſeduces his own ſoul. <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.22. Bare hearers do <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, play the ſophiſters, put tricks and fallacies upon themſelves. So v. 26. <hi>He that bridleth not his tongue,</hi> (and ſuch ordinarily is the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maliſt, bitter, railing, cenſorious) <hi>but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving his own heart, his Religion is vain:</hi> And what greater madneſs than for a man to cheat himſelf? Lay this home, and aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate your condition by it: Wretch that I am! I think to deceive God and the world, but I ſhall find at laſt that I have deceived
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:98196:69"/>
my own ſoul:<note place="margin">Pſa. 125.5</note> Will not God both find me out in theſe crooked wayes, and turn me out with the workers of iniquity? <hi>He that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verteth his wayes, ſhall be known,</hi> Prov. 10.9. <hi>The ſelf-flatterers iniquity ſhall be found hateful,</hi> Pſal. 36.21. Can I carry it ſo cloſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that God ſhall not find me out? Doth not his eye pierce, and his eye-lids try the children of men? Doth he not ſet our ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret ſins in the light of his countenance? Is there not a wo to them that dig deep to hide their ſins (as well as their counſels) from the Lord?<note place="margin">Iſa. 29.15, 16.</note> Thus labour to make thy heart ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of this ſin.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It is a ſin of evil influence upon others. Warm and lively Chriſtians are the great bleſſings of the places where they live; their zeal provokes many, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.2. But a dead and heartleſs profeſſion (eſpecially if of any eminency in the Church) puts a ſtop to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers who are apt to come up to their mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and there to reſt. The whole Army made a ſtand at <hi>Amaſa</hi>'s dead body;<note place="margin">2 Sam 20.12.</note> ſo do many at one dead Chriſtian. How may a dead and formal Miniſter or Maſter of a Family, read his own in the Temper of his People or Family? As face anſwers face in a glaſs, ſo for the moſt part doth the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion and temper of the Followers, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:98196:69"/>
that of their Leaders. Aggravate thy ſin by this conſideration upon thy own heart. Vile wretch that I am! how many do I hinder in heaven's way? how doth my formality give occaſion to ſome to think there is no reality in Religion; and to others to reſt in the ſame temper? Were I a better Leader, my People, Family, Neighbours would be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Followers: If they periſh in that ſin, how juſtly may their Blood be charged up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my head?</p>
               <p n="5">5. It is a ſin that inſenſibly hardens the heart; every ſin is of that nature, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.13. But as none is (I think) more deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, ſo ſcarce any more hardning. One or two duties cuſtomarily and formally done, will be found mightily deadning and indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing the heart to other duties afterward: By Formality in prayer, you may in time pray away both your Graces and Gifts; ſo you may by cuſtomary hearing, hear your ſelves quite deaf to all Gods counſels.<note place="margin">2 Tim. 1.6</note> This makes the heart of many like the trodden path, or neather Milſtone. Formality is a lazy ſin; it doth not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, blow up the Gifts and Graces of Gods Spirit, and ſo the Fire goes out. Habits of lazineſs are hardly ſhaken off, as we ſee in common Beggars; indulging a lazy temper, (which
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:98196:70"/>
is the Formaliſts ſin) muſt needs encreaſe it. 'Tis the Formaliſts frame, that of the ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, <hi>Prov.</hi> 6.10. and 26.14. <hi>Yet a little ſleep,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ver. 11.</note> &amp;c.—And what is ſaid of him, may well be applied hither, <hi>So ſhall thy poverty come as an armed man</hi>—By this lazy, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal temper, ſpiritual poverty invades and ſeizes upon the ſoul. Beſides, this ſin, as it hath a natural, ſo a judiciary tendency to hardneſs of heart; <hi>i. e.</hi> it provokes God to give up to obduration;<note place="margin">Luk. 19.26.</note> From him that hath not (ſo as to improve) ſhall be taken even that he hath, or ſeems to have. God will ſay to ſuch in his juſt Judgment, Sleep on, and take your reſt; and as that great Commander, finding his Sentinel aſleep, run him thorow, ſaying, <hi>Dead I found him, &amp; dead I leave him.</hi> Thus God deals with the lazy, formal, ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſh Chriſtian. Work this alſo on thy heart.</p>
               <p n="6">6. It is a ſin that broodeth, hatcheth, cheriſheth many other; Pride, Self-confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, Contempt of others, are the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral products of it. Upon account of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant courſe of formal duties, men are apt to encourage themſelves in ſin; ſee <hi>Jer.</hi> 7.8, 9, 10. 'Tis ſtoried of one (an <hi>Italian</hi> as I remember) who us'd to patter over his pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in the morning, and then challenge the Devil to do his worſt. Let but a Formaliſt
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:98196:70"/>
obſerve his own heart, and he ſhall find, That when he hath done ſomething more then ordinary in a way of duty, he is apt to draw encouragements thence of being more looſe afterward. Set this home: Oh what a Viper have I harbour'd in my boſome! How many ſins hath this one ſin let in, and drawn me into, <hi>&amp;c?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. It's a ſin that brings both the ſureſt and ſoareſt deſtruction. To ſuch is that cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting word of our Saviour directed, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.33. <hi>Ye Serpents, ye generation of Vipers; how can you eſcape the damnation of Hell?</hi> Hypocrites are Leaders in the Black Roll, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24. laſt. And as diſſembled Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is double iniquity, ſo ſhall it have a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble portion of Miſery. Theſe things I have ſuggeſted to help you in aggravating this ſin upon your own ſouls; it were eaſie to add many more, but any one of theſe laid cloſe to the Conſcience, will through the bleſſing of God, make the Soul groan un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the weight of this ſin.</p>
               <p>This is the ſum of the firſt ſtep which a ſoul is to take in order to cure; Get a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing ſight, and humbling ſenſe of thy ſin; and would but the Lord bring on the Work thus far; could I but ſee your hands on your loins, could I but find you (<hi>Ephraim</hi>-like)
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:98196:71"/>
ſmiting upon your thigh, aſhamed, confounded; were you but throughly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of the guilt, and ſenſible of the weight of this ſin, how hopeful might I be of effecting the Cure?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Direct. </seg>2</label> When it is thus (or rather, that it may be thus) with thee, make thy addreſſes to God in way of humble confeſſion, and fervent petition. But to hint ſomething briefly:</p>
               <p n="1">1. Fall down before the Lord in the ſhame and grief of thy own Soul, making ſelf-condemning Acknowledgments, and aggravated Confeſſions of this ſin. Thou that haſt been hitherto a proud Phariſee,<note place="margin">Luk. 18.13</note> now become an humble Publican. Learn <hi>Davids</hi> poſture, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.3. This is a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular way to get thy own heart affected; for indeed, it's a principal end of confeſſion; we do not confeſs ſin to inform God, but to humble and ſhame our ſelves. In confeſſion thou mayeſt uſe the forementioned aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Add Petition to confeſſion; beg a more lively ſenſe of this ſin; for it is not all thy own aggravating this ſin upon thy ſoul, that will make thee feel it to purpoſe, till God take it, and ſet it upon thy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; 'tis the Spirit of God that muſt to purpoſe convince of ſin, <hi>John</hi> 16.8. the
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:98196:71"/>
ſins which look but as Moats, will appear Beams in that Light which the Spirit of God darts into the Soul. Beg Contrition alſo, that acceptable Sacrifice of a broken heart, muſt be of Gods own preparing, the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row which is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: according to God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.10—muſt be from God, <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.10. Beg pardon with the <hi>Pſalmiſt, Pſ.</hi> 51.1. Fitly may you uſe his Petition and Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.11. <hi>Pardon my ſin—for it is great;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 18.13</note> and take up the Publicans Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture and Petition, ſmite on your breaſt, and ſay, <hi>The Lord be merciful to me a ſinner.</hi> Beg ſtrength againſt this ſin; pray for Truth in the inward parts; pray as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.80. <hi>Make my heart ſound in thy ſtatutes, that I may never be confounded.</hi> Lord, I have the Lineaments, put into me the Life of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian; make me what I ſeem, leſt at laſt I be found what I would not; and here, take heed you be not formal in confeſſing and praying againſt your formality; a hypocrite, that hath got the Art to confeſs his hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie in hypocriſie, and ſeems to be diſpleaſed with himſelf for that ſin, when he is not ſo indeed, may well have <hi>[Lord have mercy]</hi> written upon his door.</p>
               <p>Labour to get thoſe things which are the <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Direct. </seg>3</label> very Life and Eſſence of a Chriſtian;
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:98196:72"/>
thoſe things which are conſtituent of, and difference a Chriſtian from all others. Some of theſe things have been hinted already, in ſhewing what a Formaliſt wants; I ſhall touch upon them here, and add more. In general, Content not your ſelves to act as Chriſtians, or in doing what a Chriſtian doth; 'tis one thing to be and do as a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and another to be a Chriſtian. There are eſpecially five things which conſtitute, and are, as it were, ingredient into the very Eſſence of a Chriſtian.</p>
               <p n="1">1. A ſound conviction of, and deep hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation for ſin. This (as you heard be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) the Formaliſt wants; this is the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Foundation of all that ſaving-work which the Spirit of God doth upon the Soul, <hi>John</hi> 16.8. This is the ordinary forerunner of true ſolid Comfort: Convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and Contrition are the inlets and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratives to Conſolation. Here begun the work upon thoſe three thouſand Converts, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.37. upon <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 7.9. And though its wrought in ſome inſenſibly, or with leſs noiſe and horror; yet it is wrought in all really, who are ſaved in Gods ordinary way, and who are truly wrought upon.</p>
               <p>Labour then to feel ſin your heavieſt bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den; and that not onely ſome one or few
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:98196:72"/>
ſins of your life,<note place="margin">2 Chron. 32.26.</note> but eſpecially your heart-pollutions; be humbled (with <hi>Hezekiah</hi>) for the pride of your heart, and ſo for other inward luſts; yea, let your humiliation reach to your very duties; be aſhamed at their deficiency and defilements; labour to ſee and be ſenſible, that all your righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is as a filthy rag;<note place="margin">Iſa. 64.6.</note> and ceaſe not to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the ſtreams; until you are come to the Spring-head, <hi>viz.</hi> the corruption of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and here ſit down and weep, as the <hi>Jews</hi> by the Rivers of <hi>Babylon:</hi> Never think your conviction and humiliation right, till you arrive at this, <hi>viz.</hi> A clear ſight, and deep abiding ſenſe of the univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal pollution of your nature, and the utter inability to any thing truly and ſpiritually good. Thus you muſt, as it were, begin the work again, raze all other, and lay this as a ſound foundation; he that hath this, hath the root of the matter in him.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Labour after a total abnegation of your own righteouſneſs, duties, priviledges, performances—This is eſſential to a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian; in that brief, but full deſcription of a ſincere Chriſtian, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.3. this is one of the three Ingredients, <hi>To put no confidence in the fleſh.</hi> The firſt Leſſon in Chriſt's School, is <hi>Self-denial, Matt.</hi> 16.24. We muſt
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:98196:73"/>
learn that counſel, <hi>Luke</hi> 17.10. to <hi>acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg our ſelves unprofitable ſervants;</hi> 'tis one of he hardeſt Tasks, but exceeding neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary. True Grace, and Chriſtian Religion, is, <hi>[perpetua naturae violentia]</hi> a doing vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to our ſelves, thwarting our paſſions, depluming our ſelves of all thoſe. Feathers wherewith we are wont to ſtrut, and in which we have prided our ſelves. We muſt learn to acknowledg with the Prophet,<note place="margin">Iſa. 64.6.</note> That all our righteouſneſs is but as a filthy rag; that our beſt Duties, or ſeem ng Graces, are in themſelves but a beautiful Abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and to truſt in them, is but to go a cleaner way to Hell. And what ſhould hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der from this ſelf-denial? What is thy righteouſneſs more (nay, is it not in many reſpects leſs) then that of the Scribes and Phariſees? Read <hi>Luke</hi> 18.10, 11—and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare; yet ver. 14. the ſelf-abaſing Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can went away more juſtified than the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſee; that is, the Phariſee was not at all ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified; for there is not <hi>magis &amp; minus</hi> in Juſtification Away then with all thy proud ſelf-reflections; think but how ſtrict a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition ſhall be made at the day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and how piercing the eyes of the Judg will be; and then conſider whether thou ſhalt be able to ſtand before him in
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:98196:73"/>
thy own rags; and if thou wilt not be able then to ſtand, why ſhouldſt thou now glory in them? Oh! ſurely God can ſee beams in thoſe duties, where thou canſt not diſcern moats; and will diſcover blemiſhes, where thou conceiteſt there is the greateſt beauty.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Endeavour a cordial cloſe with Chriſt upon Goſpel-tearms. Here lies the main to which the two former are preparatory. This was <hi>Paul</hi>'s great deſire,<note place="margin">Phil. 3.9.</note> 
                  <hi>To be found in Chriſt</hi>—Get therefore that precious Grace of Faith, which is the hand wherewith thou muſt accept Chriſt; whatever thou haſt, if this be wanting, thou ſhalt certainly periſh; <hi>John</hi> 3.18, 36. The grand Enquiry at the great Day will be, Whether you believed or no; though it's true, your work will be look't into, but thoſe as the proofs and evidences of the ſincerity of your Faith: There will be no ſtanding before the Judg, except him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf be thy Advocate; and this he will not be, but upon thy cordial acceptance of him now. On make out for Chriſt; cry out, Give me Chriſt, or I dye. And that you may get Chriſt, you muſt not (as <hi>Peter</hi>) gird your Coat (your own righteouſneſs) to you; but as <hi>Bartimeus,</hi> caſt it from you. Neither think that a blind, bold, adventurous ruſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon Chriſt, a meer adherence to him,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:98196:74"/>
or a confident perſwaſion of his good-will towards you in particular, is the all, or main of this Faith and Acceptance I am preſſing; (this miſtake will, I fear, be the ruine of Thouſands,) There muſt be an abſolute re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignment of thy ſelf to Chriſt, as well as reliance on him: 'Tis a <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a groſs and grievous miſtake, to think that the ſtrength of Faith lyes in the ſtrength of a man's Fancy or Imagination, or of his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion that Chriſt dyed for him in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar: True Faith gives as well as takes; when you ſend for a Phyſician, and he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakes and promiſes your cure, 'tis ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed you accept of him, and reſolve to follow his Preſcriptions, elſe you may miſcarry: To accept Chriſt as your Saviour &amp; Soul-Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian, neceſſarily includes your giving up your ſelves to follow his Preſcriptions, elſe you but diſſemble with him. This I hint to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent miſtakes about the nature of true Faith, (which are too ordinary.) Well, if thou who art yet a Formaliſt, wouldſt be a Chriſtian indeed, get out of all, and accept Chriſt as tendred in the Goſpel.</p>
               <p n="4">4. See that thou have a thorow change of heart, <hi>Eph</hi> 4.23. <hi>Be renewed in the Spirit of your mind.</hi> 1 Theſ. 5.23. <hi>Sanctified through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out,</hi> 'Tis not building on the old Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:98196:74"/>
repairing and decking up the old man, will ſerve turn? 'Tis not putting a new piece upon the old Garment; all is depraved in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam;</hi> All muſt be renew'd in Chriſt; it's no leſs then a new Creation, that makes a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. That which is born of the fleſh,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5. 17</note> (even the beſt of it, is no better than fleſh, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.3, 6. The beſt of a carnal man, is carnal; no man is born a Chriſtian. There muſt be a <hi>putting off the old man, and putting on the new man, Eph.</hi> 4.22, 24. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.9, 10.<note place="margin">Pſal. 4 5.10 <hi>Bialt.</hi>
                  </note> a forgetting and forſaking thy own People and Fathers houſe; that is, as one well gloſſes, <hi>Quic quid corruptionis ex utero afferimus aut quaecun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ex placâ inſtitutione nobis adhaerent:</hi> Whatever corruption we derived from the Womb, or contracted by Education, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Well, ſee that not only the branches of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption be lopt off, but the root digg'd up; let ſin be not only left, but loath'd; let duty be not only done, but delighted. See that the change be not only in the face of your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations, but in the frame of your hearts, and bent of your affections; and ſee that it be the whole inward man, not underſtanding only illightned, or affections enlarg'd; but each faculty having its proper work of San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification wrought upon it, and above all, the Will brought to a chearful ſubmiſſion to, and compliance with the Will &amp; Commands
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:98196:75"/>
of God, even in thoſe things that are moſt oppoſite to your natural inclinations. This is a fourth Eſſential in a Chriſtian.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Endeavour livelineſs, vigour and ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in every duty; content not thy ſelf, till thou haſt got thy heart engag'd in duty. I bid thee not lay aſide duty; (nay, rather be more frequent) but withall, more fervent and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in it. Hear and practiſe; pray in the ſpirit; turn thy dead and heartleſs confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, into heart-breaking acknowledgments; thy formal petitions, into earneſt groans and breathings of ſoul, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and withall, ſee that thy end in all be right, <hi>viz.</hi> Gods glory, and thy ſouls advantage. Rectitude of ends, is a great piece of ſincerity: Oh, this is very eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential to a Chriſtian, not onely to do duty, but to be lively, vigorous and right-ended in it; not onely to do it, but to do ſomthing by it, and receive ſomething through it; and that it may be thus, make Conſcience of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſneſs and livelineſs in the ſmalleſt duties, in thy daily Family-duties, yea, in thy very begging a bleſſing upon the creature. Forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity creeps in at our ordinary and leſſer du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and by degrees mixes it ſelf with our greater; out it (as much as poſſible) of your common and ordinary, and there is leſs dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger it ſhould ſpoil your extraordinary duties.</p>
               <p>And thus I have in theſe five particulars,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:98196:75"/>
included (I think) m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt of that which is eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential to a Chriſtian. Oh that the Lord would perſwade your hearts to endeavour after them, and that they may be found in every ſoul of you! Theſe are they that do ſpecifie and conſtitute a Chriſtian indeed, and that do diſtinguiſh him from, and ſet him above all others in the world; get theſe, and you are more then Formaliſts; but get them all; the third cannot be without the firſt and ſecond; nor can the fourth and fifth, really be without the third; but where all theſe are found in conjunction, that ſoul may undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly conclude its real Chriſtianity.</p>
               <p>As a ſingular help to rowſe thee out of <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Direct. </seg>4</label> Formality, repreſent to thy thoughts &amp; me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations, the nature of God, eſpecially in thoſe awakening Attributes, his <hi>Spirituality,</hi> his <hi>Omniſcience, Omnipreſence, &amp;c.</hi> together with the <hi>dreadfulneſs of the day of judgment. Formality</hi> is the <hi>ſouls ſluggiſhneſs,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it needs thoſe helps that are moſt <hi>awak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</hi> And oh how would the lively repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation of theſe things, ſtartle you out of this <hi>drowſie temper!</hi> Is not God a <hi>Spirit?</hi> and <hi>Spirits</hi> are active; and how ill do they that are themſelves active &amp; vigorous, brook the lazines of others? Again, <hi>Is not Gods eye upon me? Is he not preſent in a ſpecial man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to thoſe that are in his ſervice? and muſt
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:98196:76"/>
not ſuch a cold and careleſs temper be highly diſpleaſing to him?</hi> Again, <hi>How ſhall I be able to ſtand before the Tribunal? Will not my For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality be then diſcovered? will not the care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs performance, as well as total neglect of du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, be enquir'd into, and ſeverely puniſhed at that day?</hi> Such workings as theſe will be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the heart that lies under the lively ſenſe of thoſe things; and they muſt needs put life into thy duties, and put thee out of thy dull and ſluggiſh temper.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Direct. </seg>5</label> Get a holy jealouſie and ſuſpition of thy own heart; watch it as thou wouldſt watch a lazy or unfaithful ſervant: Our hearts will do no longer then they are watcht, and task<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and followed; we muſt be winding them higher continually; if we let them ſlacken never ſo little, drowſineſs ſteals upon them; it muſt be a jealous eye, and ſtrict hand over them, that muſt keep them waking. Deal therefore with your hearts, as <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 103.1, 2. <hi>Bleſs the Lord, O my ſoul, and all that is within me</hi>—He calls upon his ſoul, thus muſt we,<note place="margin">Prov. 6.9, 10.</note> be often jogging them; ſay not, <hi>A little more ſleep, a little more ſlumber</hi>—but rather, <hi>Why ſleepeſt thou, O ſluggard? When wilt thou ariſe out of thy ſleep?</hi> Yea, when they ſeem to be moſt wakeful and active, there is need to watch them, eſpecially after a duty done with more than ordinary fervor;
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:98196:76"/>
intenſneſs of action, cauſeth wearineſs, and wearineſs inclines to ſleep and ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſhneſs.</p>
               <p>Earneſtly beg the continuance of <hi>lively</hi>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Direct. </seg>6</label> &amp; <hi>quickning Ordinances,</hi> and beg <hi>life</hi> and <hi>quickning</hi> into thoſe <hi>Ordinances.</hi> 1. Beg <hi>live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> and <hi>quickning Ordinances.</hi> They are the <hi>means</hi> which God hath appointed to beget and keep life in the ſoul; the word is, The immortal ſeed whereby ſouls are begotten to God, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.23. But if this and other Ordinances loſe their livelineſs, by a dead, hearteſs, formal management; they will inſtead of rouſing us out, lull us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep in our formality. <hi>Cor non faciunt quae non habent:</hi> How can thoſe Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances make hearty Chriſtians, which have no heart in them? Ordinances that are not good,<note place="margin">Ezek. 20.25.</note> and ſtatutes whereby a ſoul cannot live, are amongſt the ſaddeſt of judgments: Dead forms are like the ſtone at the foot of the Bird, which hinders it from the firſt uſe of its wing: Alſo how prone is the laſt age of the world to fall into this drowſie temper? We have need of the moſt lively Ordinances, and all too little to keep us waking: Dull, heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Preaching, Prayers, or other Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances will charm the Soul into a dead ſleep, and will be as a ſoft Pillow under
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:98196:77"/>
the elbow of drowſie ſinners; and this (I am perſwaded) is the great reaſon why the multitude dote on their old forms; becauſe they will break no bones, they will not come near the quick: Men love to be rock'd &amp; huſh'd aſleep in their Formality: Oh, but if ever you would get from under this corruption, it muſt be by quickning Ordinances: Oh let us beg of God, that his Worſhip may be diſpenſed in that way that is moſt advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious to the putting ſouls into, and keeping them in a waking poſture.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Beg life and quickning into Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances; the beſt Ordinances have no power in them, if they be not quickned by the Spirit. They are but like the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet's ſtaff, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 4.31. We ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſtand upon our feet, though the Word bid us ſtand, if the Spirit do not enter into us, and ſet us upon our feet, <hi>Ezek</hi> 2.1, 2. The weapons of our war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare are mighty, but it muſt be through God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4. If we muſt have heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Ordinances, earneſt Prayer will ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther procure better, or a bleſſing upon what we have.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Direct. </seg>7</label> Get into, and frequent the ſociety of warm and hearty Chriſtians: they are like ſticks on fire, which wil kindle others that are put to them, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.2. Your zeal hath provoked many: If there be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:98196:77"/>
ſpark under the aſhes, they will help to blow it up: If thou haſt not the opportunity of conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing with living Chriſtians, yet converſe in the Scriptures, and other Records, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re the lives of ſuch are Recorded for thy Im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tation, they will ſhame thee out of thy Formality: they will mightily quicken thee, if there be any thing of true piety in thy heart: their zeal, forwardneſs, diligence in duty, their care and conſcientiouſneſs will put thee on in heavens way; Example is often more prevailing then Precepts Therefore the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt enjoins ſubjection, chaſtity, meekneſs, and other Chriſtian vertues, to the Wife, that if the unbelieving H sband obey not the Word, he may be won by the W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ves converſation.</p>
               <p>Think often in what manner you hope to ſerve <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Direct. </seg>8</label> God in glory; and how the Angels and glorified Saints do now ſerve him: are they now, or will you then be ſo cold, careleſs and heartleſs as you now a e? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.20 The Angels excel in ſtrength, doing his Commandments; and the glorified Saints, (<hi>Rev.</hi> 4.8 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5.8, 9, 13.) <hi>Reſt not day and night, ſaying, holy, holy, holy, Lord God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty</hi>— Doſt thou hope to be of that bleſſed ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, and yet act ſo unlike them now? Should we not labour to be, and act, as we hope one day to be and act? It ill be ſeems him who hopes one day to j in in conſort with that heavenly quire, to be ſo unskilful and heartleſs in the ſervice of God, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.11. It was <hi>Pauls</hi> endeavour and ambition, it by any means, to attain to the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the dead, <hi>i.e.</hi> to that meaſure and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection which he hoped then to arrive at. True, we are clogg'd with fleſh and corruption; 'tis impoſſible that our ſervices ſhould be ſo pure and
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:98196:78"/>
undefiled; but we ſhould be aſpiring towards it; we ſhould do violence to the fleſh, that we may ſerve God in the Spirit: How unſuitable are cold, worthleſs and lifeleſs ſervices to the eternal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward? Let your hopes of Glory, and your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations to be of that bleſſed ſociety, quicken and wind up you hearts to a high pitch of zeal and fervency; ſo it did the believing Jews, <hi>Act.</hi> 26.7. To the which promiſe our 12 Tribes inſtantly ſerving God day and night, hope to come.<note place="margin">Heb. 6.11, 12.</note> Let us ſhew the ſame diligence to the full aſſurance of hope, unto the end: Let us not be ſloathful, but followers of them, who through Faith and Patience inherit the promiſes. Thus I have propoſed ſome Remedies, which (if the Lord bleſs unto you) may be effectual, both to bring on thoſe who are meer Formaliſts, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſincere Chriſtians, and to quicken thoſe that are Chriſtians indeed, to more vigour and livelineſs in the practice of all Chriſtian Duties. It were eaſie to have added many more; but I ſhall intreat you to think of theſe, and work them upon your hearts, and you ſhall, by the bleſſing of God, find them helpful to the end for which they were propounded. <hi>And now, Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, I commend you to God, and to the word of his Grace,—Act.</hi> 20 32.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:98196:78"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
